我的光头脑袋瓜还管用吗？
Do I have an original thought in my head? My bald head?
如果我能快乐一点 也许就不会掉头发
Maybe if I were happier, my hair wouldn't be falling out.
人生苦短 我得好好利用
Life is short. I need to make the most of it.
人生今日方开始
Today is the first day of the rest of my life.
我是个行尸走肉
I'm a walking cliche.
我得去看医生 检查我的腿
I really need to go to the doctor and have my leg checked.
我腿有毛病 长了瘤
There's something wrong. A bump.
牙医生也打电话来 我已经赖很久了
The dentist called again. I'm way overdue.
如果我不再推推脱脱 我会更快乐
If I stopped putting things off, I'd be happier.
肥屁股整天坐着 屁股要是不这么肥，我会更快乐
All I do is sit on my fat ass. If my ass wasn't fat, I'd be happier.
这些衬衫的下摆 也不会老是塞不进去
I wouldn't have to wear these shirts with the tails out all the time.
不是盖的
Like that's fooling anyone.
肥屁股，我又该慢跑了 一天5英里
Fat ass. I should start jogging again. Five miles a day.
这回决不黄牛 甚至去攀岩
Really do it this time. Maybe rock climbing.
我要洗心革面
I need to turn my life around.
该怎么办？ 我需要恋爱
What do I need to do? I need to fall in love.
我要交个女友
I need to have a girlfriend.
多读点书，充实自己
I need to read more, improve myself.
学俄语好了 ，或者别的？
What if I learned Russian or something?
还是学一样乐器？ 或者学讲中文
Or took up an instrument? I could speak Chinese.
那我就成了会说中文 又会吹双簧管的编剧
I would be the screenwriter who speaks Chinese. And plays the oboe.
那可神了 我要剪个短发
That would be cool. I should get my hair cut short.
不再自欺欺人 让人以为我不秃头
Stop trying to fool everyone into thinking I have a full head of hair.
真够可悲 真实点，拿出自信来
How pathetic is that? Just be real. Confident.
女人不就吃这套？
Isn't that what women are attracted to?
男人不必好看
Men don't have to be attractive.
但世风变了 ，尤其是最近
But that's not true, especially these days.
男人的压力已经不比女人少
Almost as much pressure on men as there is on women these days.
我为何要受迫害 认为自己没有存在价值？
Why should I be made to feel I have to apologize for my existence?
也许只是自己脑筋打结
Maybe it's my brain chemistry.
或许这正是我的问题所在 脑筋打结
Maybe that's what's wrong with me: bad chemistry.
我的失落和焦虑 可以归结为脑筋不平衡...
All my problems and anxiety can be reduced to a chemical imbalance...
或是某种神经原不来电
...or some kind of misfiring synapses.
真该去看个医生
I need to get help for that.
但再看医生也是一样丑
But I'll still be ugly, though.
那是无救了的
Nothing's gonna change that.
闭嘴！ 闭嘴！
Shut up! Shut up!
“变恼”的场景 1998年夏
今天让我们真正解决 摄影机问题
Let's really try today to solve our camera problems.
约翰马可维奇 主演
要把中间空档时间减到最小
Keep between- take time at an absolute minimum.
这些面罩有够热，知道吗？
These masks are really hot. Okay?
大家全都听清楚了
l wanna be very well- heard on that from everybody.
别打混 除非剧情真的需要
Don't futz unless it's absolutely important to the shot, okay?
我不是说自己 我在说所有在场的人...
l don't say that for me. l say that for the people sitting here...
- 谢谢你，约翰 - 穿着沉重橡皮的人
- Thank you, John. - ...in the rubber.
- 我喜欢我的洋装，行吗？ - 很好
- l like my dress. Okay? - Very good.
现在，各位 请听劝告
So now, folks, you better heed that advice.
唐麦史密 首席助理导演
准备拍片
Stand by for picture.
蓝斯亚可 放映师
让她在桌边转动 稍远一点
Have her rotate around the table a little bit further.
查理考夫曼 编剧
先等我们清场
Hold on until we're clear.
你，你挡住视线了 请你离开舞台好吗？
You. You're in the eyeline. Can you please get off the stage?
对，把6英尺的拿进来
Yeah, just bring in the six- footer.
我在干吗？ 今天根本不该来的
What am I doing here? Why did I bother to come here today?
根本没人认识我
Nobody even seems to know my name.
我已经在世上40年了 却还是啥都不懂
I've been on this planet for 40 years, and I don't understand a single thing.
为什么我在这里？ 我怎会在这里？
Why am I here? How did I get here?
加州好莱坞
早在40亿又40年前
我的腿很痛 ，我担心是癌症
My leg hurts. I wonder if it's cancer.
长了瘤，又开始流汗了 别流汗
There's a bump. I'm starting to sweat. Stop sweating.
我一定要止住流汗
I've got to stop sweating.
她会看见我额头滴汗吗？
Can she see it dripping down my forehead?
她在观察我的发根 她认为我秃头...
She looked at my hairline. She thinks I'm bald. She- -
我们认为你很棒
We think you're great.
谢了 ，你真会说话
Thanks. That's nice to hear.
我们都爱死变脑的剧本了
We all just loved the Malkovich script.
- 多谢， 多谢... - 见解很独到
- Thanks. Thanks.... - Such a unique voice.
我真想到你的头脑里面看看
Boy, l'd love to find a portal into your brain.
相信我，一点也不好玩
Trust me, it's no fun.
告诉我 你对这个疯狂计划的看法
So tell me your thoughts on this crazy little project of ours.
首先，这是本好书
First, l think it's a great book.
兰花贼 苏丝欧琳
- 老许是个搞笑角色，对吧？ - 正确
- Laroche is a fun character, isn't he? - Absolutely.
而欧琳使得兰花更加迷人
And Orlean makes orchids so fascinating.
加上，她对佛州的冥想 和偷采兰花...
Plus, her musings on Florida and orchid poaching...
的印地安人，简直是 棒透的纽约客题材
...lndians. lt's just- -  lt's great, sprawling New Yorker stuff.
我必须保持它的原有水准
l'd want to remain true to that.
我希望影片自己活起来 而不是...
l'd wanna let the movie exist, rather than be...
- 硬梆梆的照本宣科 - 好啊
- ...artificially plot- driven. - Great.
我也不明白这到底是啥意思
l guess l'm not exactly sure what that means.
我也不清楚它的真正涵义
l'm not sure l know what that means either.
我只希望好莱坞的积习 不至于毁了它
l just don't wanna ruin it by making it a Hollywood thing. You know?
变成一部 兰花争夺战之类的电影
Like...an orchid heist movie or something, you know?
或把兰花偷换成罂粟花...
Or changing the orchids into poppies...
而演变成毒品追逐战
...and making it about drug running, you know?
- 绝对正确 - 为什么就不能...
- Definitely. - Why can't there be a movie...
纯粹拍一部花卉电影？
...simply about flowers?
我想我们正是这个意思
l guess we thought that maybe...
苏丝欧琳和老许 可以相恋，而且...
...Susan Orlean and Laroche could fall in love, and- -
这么说吧，就好比 我不希望充斥着性欲...
Okay. But l'm saying, it's like, l don't wanna cram in sex...
枪枝或飞车追逐...
...or guns or car chases...
或是片中角色...
...you know, or characters, you know...
洞悉了深邃的人生哲学
...learning profound life lessons.
或成长 或相互接纳对方...
Or growing, or coming to like each other...
或突破万难 最后终于功成名立，我是说...
...or overcoming obstacles to succeed in the end, you know? l mean- -
这本书不是这类故事...
The book isn't like that...
真实人生也并非如此 事实如此，而且...
...and life isn't like that. You know, it just isn't. And....
我很坚持这个理念
l feel very strongly about this.
纽约客杂志 三年前
约翰老许是个高个子 细长像竹竿...
John Laroche is a tall guy, skinny as a stick...
眼光冷漠 双肩微垂...
...pale- eyed, slouch- shouldered...
轮廓俊酷 虽然烂光了满口门牙
...sharply handsome, despite the fact he's missing all his front teeth.
两年前我去佛州 替纽约客写一篇报导
I went to Florida two years ago to write a piece for The New Yorker.
那是在读到一篇一个白人 和三个印地安人的文章之后...
It was after reading a small article about a white man and three Seminole men...
他们因为 偷盗稀有兰花而被捕...
...arrested with rare orchids they'd stolen out of a place...
偷采自叫做法喀哈契浅滩 的州立保育区
...called the Fakahatchee Strand State Preserve.
佛州29号州公路 两年前
物竞天择之下每种物种 只有最优秀者得以生存...
As natural selection works solely by
这是达尔文说的
and for the good of each being...
躯体和心智的天赋 会趋于演化到完美
...all corporeal and mental endowments will tend to progress towards perfection.
思考理解千头万绪的知识 很有意思...
It's interesting to contemplate an entangled bank....
鬼兰
Polyrrhiza lindenii.
一个鬼魂
A ghost.
罗素，采下她
Cut her down, Russell.
法喀哈契浅滩 州立保育区
- 早 - 嗨
- Morning. - Hey.
可以请问各位 你们布袋里装的是啥？
May l ask you gentlemen what you have in those pillowcases?
当然可以问
Yes, sir, you absolutely may.
- 那就请说吧 - 好吧
- Okay, then, l'm asking. - Well, okay, then.
来瞧瞧
Let's see.
这里有5种凤梨科植物...
We've got five kinds of bromeliad...
一棵胡椒草 九株各色兰花
...one peperomia, nine orchid varieties.
你知道 总共有130种植物
You know, about 1 30 plants all told.
是我的同事们 采自这片沼泽
Which my colleagues here removed from the swamp.
你们明白从州有土地上 采摘或捕猎是违法的？
You're aware it's illegal to remove plants or animals from state- owned land?
是啊，而且不要忘记...
Yeah, and don't forget...
这些花草都是濒临绝种植物 每棵都不例外
...these plants are all endangered, sir. Every one of them.
这正是问题重点所在 这里是州立保育区
Well, exactly. That's exactly the issue. This is a state preserve.
是的，长官
Yes, sir. lt is.
- 但是... - 我同事都是塞米诺印第安人
- But... - My colleagues are all Seminole lndians.
我没有告诉你吗？ 你一定很清楚...
Did l mention that? You're familiar, l'm sure...
佛州控告詹姆比利的案子
...with the State of Florida v. James E. Billie?
因此即使塞米诺酋长比利 猎杀了佛州黑豹...
So you know that even though Seminole Chief Billie killed a Florida panther...
多少？全世界只剩40只吧？
...one of what, 40 in the entire world?
- 40只 - 40只
- Forty. - Forty.
州方也奈何不了他...
The state couldn't successfully prosecute him...
你知道吗， 因为他是印地安人 他就有这个权利
...because, you know, he's an lndian, and it's his right.
虽然你我白人保护主义者 极力反对他的行径
As repugnant as you and l, as white conservationists, might find his actions.
- 可是... - 更别提其他的失败尝试...
- But... - Not to mention the failed attempts...
有3次企图起诉 塞米诺人采摘棕榈蕨
...on three occasions to prosecute Seminoles for poaching palm fronds.
我猜他们是拿来铺设 传统鸡舍的屋顶
Which l believe they use to thatch the roofs of their traditional chickee huts.
你想想看？ 是鸡舍的屋顶，对吧？
How about that? With the chickee huts, right?
没错，我们正是用那造鸡舍的
Yeah, he's right. That's exactly what we use them for. Chickee huts.
是，但我也不能...
Yeah, but l don't- -
我还不能放你们走
l can't let you fellas leave yet.
- 你们先别走喔 - 好啊
- Just hold on there a minute. - Okay.
查理，是你吗？
Charles, is that you?
你吃过午餐吗？
Did you eat lunch?
我吃了冰箱的虾肉沙拉 那是你的吗？
l had that shrimp cocktail in the fridge. Was it yours?
最好不是，我也忘了 于是我吃掉了
l hope not. l couldn't remember, so l ate it.
也许我们今后应该 写上名字
Maybe we should write our names on our food items from now on.
- 你怎么了？ - 背不舒服
- What's with you? - My back.
查理，你一定会很开心 我准备尽快搬出去
Charles, you'll be glad. l have a plan to get me out of your house, pronto.
- 工作才是计划，你找到工作吗？ - 听好了
- A job is a plan. ls your plan a job? - Drum roll, please.
我要成为编剧 和你一样
l'm gonna be a screenwriter. Like you.
你一定觉得 我又在做发财梦...
l know you think this is just one of my ''get rich quick'' schemes...
但这次我很认真的
...but l'm doing it right this time.
我参加了一个3日讲习 而且只要500大洋
l'm taking a three- day seminar, and it's only 500 bucks.
编剧讲习根本是狗屁
Screenwriting seminars are bullshit.
理论上我也同意 但这一个与众不同
ln theory, l agree with you. But this one's different.
业界风评非常好
This one's highly regarded in the industry.
唐诺，不要跟我说“业界”
Donald, don't say ''industry.''
抱歉，我又忘了
l'm sorry. l forgot.
查理，这家伙真的懂编剧
Charles, this guy knows screenwriting.
大家远道而来 向他学艺
People come from all over to study with him.
- 我会尽快还你钱... - 我告诉你说
- l'll pay you back as soon as l... - Let me explain something.
任何人说他有 “秘方” 都是想要引人上勾...
Anybody who says he's got ''the answer'' is going to attract desperate people...
请你实际一点...
...be it in the world of religion- -
让我躺着听你解释
l just need to lie down while you explain this to me.
抱歉，我道歉
Sorry. l apologize.
请继续吧
Okay, go ahead.
- 所以... - 对不起，请说
- So... - Sorry. Okay. Go.
并没有什么规则可循
There are no rules, Donald.
如果有人硬要说有 纯粹是在...
And anybody who says there are is just, you know- -
不是规则，是原则
Not rules. Principles.
马契写道，规则只是 “你必须要这样做”
McKee writes that a rule says, ''You must do it this way.''
原则是“长久以来 已经证实有效的方法”
A principle says, ''This works and has through all remembered time.''
我要着手的剧本 是关于花卉
The script l'm starting, it's about flowers.
还不曾有人写过花卉的电影
Nobody's ever done a movie about flowers before.
- 因此没有范例可循 - 艾吉浓之花算不算？
- So there are no guidelines. - What about Flowers for Algernon?
哎呀，那写的不是花 也不是电影
Well, that's not about flowers. And it's not a movie.
抱歉，我也没看过
l'm sorry. l never saw it.
如何...？ 好吧，请继续
How...? Okay, keep going.
我只是要说 那些老师很危险...
Look, my point is that those teachers are dangerous...
如果你是想要 尝试新鲜点子
...if your goal is to try to do something new.
作家应该都有这种目标 写作是对未知世界的探索
A writer should always have that goal. Writing is a journey into the unknown.
这和打造模型飞机不同
lt's not building, you know, one of your model airplanes.
马契是前任傅布莱奖学者 查理
McKee is a former Fulbright Scholar, Charles.
你也是个傅布莱奖学者吗？
Are you a former Fulbright Scholar?
开口说话呀，带她出来 竟不敢和她说话
Say something. I dragged her here, and now I'm not saying anything.
让她发笑 说些笑话
Make her laugh. Say something funny.
我讨厌派对，艾咪 我们干嘛来这里？
l hate parties, Amelia. Why did we come here?
因为我们时髦、是潮流引领者 对吧？
Because we're hip, young trendsetters on the make, aren't we?
倒像是满地失败的痞子
More like old losers sitting on the floor, maybe.
天哪，查理，那是你吧...
Jesus, Charlie. Speak for yourself. Okay....
查理，我们想给你做媒
Charlie, we're gonna fix you up.
我们要彻底解决 查理考夫曼乱象
We're gonna solve the whole Charlie Kaufman mess for once and for all.
- 好 - 让我瞧瞧
- Okay. - Okay, let me see.
你需要什么 什么，什么？
What do you need? What, what, what?
我很高兴你写了兰花剧本
Well, l'm glad you took the orchid script.
我想它能帮助厘清你的思路
l think it will be good for you to get out of your head.
能够定下心来 想一些大自然的事情
l think it'll ground you to think about the bigger picture, about nature and stuff.
我仍然不敢相信 他们录用了我
l still can't believe they gave me that job.
那顿午餐吃得我满头大汗
l mean, after that lunch. l was sweating insanely.
我简直口无伦次一塌糊涂
l was ranting. l was a mess.
你太紧张 因为她太漂亮
You were just nervous because she was pretty.
你怎么知道她很漂亮？
How do you know she was pretty?
和你认识了8个月 我很了解你流汗的原因
After eight months of knowing you, l think l get what makes you sweat.
哎呀，管它的 你赶快继续说
Well, whatever. Well, moving on, what next?
你需要新行头 这套法兰绒衬衫...
You need a new getup. This whole flannel shirt thing...
实在不怎么样
...it's not really doing anything for you anymore.
谢谢你今晚跟我出来 艾咪
Thanks for coming out with me tonight, Amelia.
起头
To begin.
该怎么开始？
How to start?
我饿了
I'm hungry.
我需要喝咖啡
I should get coffee.
咖啡可以帮助我思考
Coffee would help me think.
但我应该先写出一些成果 然后才喝咖啡犒赏自己
But I should write something first, then reward myself with coffee.
咖啡和松糕 我需要建立主题大纲
Coffee and a muffin. Okay, so I need to establish the themes.
香蕉核桃好了
Maybe banana- nut.
松糕很不错
That's a good muffin.
采摘野兰花是要命的工作
Orchid hunting is a mortal occupation.
委内瑞拉欧林诺克河 100年以前
维多利亚时代兰花采摘 威廉阿诺...
Victorian- era orchid hunter William Arnold...
在一次采摘探险中溺死了
...drowned on a collecting expedition.
金纳巴鲁波尼尔
欧斯莫 在亚洲消失得无影无踪
Osmers vanished without a trace in Asia.
中国西双版纳
存活的奥古斯都马奎利 染患牙痛风湿胸膜炎和痢疾...
Augustus Margary survived toothache, rheumatism, pleurisy and dysentery...
却在任务完成...
...only to be murdered when he completed his mission...
到达巴哈莫时被人谋杀
...and traveled beyond Bhamo.
老许钟爱兰花，但是...
Laroche loved orchids, but I....
我比较倾向 他对冒险犯难的热爱...
I came to believe he loved the difficulty and fatality of getting them...
几乎和喜爱兰花相当
...almost as much as he loved the orchids themselves.
我成为园艺专家已经12年了
l've been a professional horticulturist for, like, 1 2 years.
佛罗里达迈阿密 6个月后
我自己拥有的苗圃 被飓风吹垮了
l owned my own plant nursery, which was destroyed by the hurricane.
我现在是植物学专业讲师
l'm a professional plant lecturer.
我发表过60多篇 有关培养植物的专题演讲
l've given over, like, 60 lectures on the cultivation of plants.
我的论文刊登在杂志上 我也出书
l'm a published author, both in magazine and book form.
我对兰花已经了若指掌...
And l have extensive experience with orchids...
包括无菌状态的 试管无性繁殖
...and the asexual micropropagation of orchids under aseptic cultures.
那是实验室的工作 和你的苗圃完全不一样
That's laboratory work. lt's not at all like your nursery work.
我简直是天资异秉无人可及
l'm probably the smartest person l know.
- 谢谢你 - 甭客气
- Thank you. - You're very welcome.
是老许吗？ 我是苏丝欧琳
Mr. Laroche? l'm Susan Orlean.
我替纽约客杂志写文章 那是一本...
l'm a writer for The New Yorker. lt's a magazine that- -
纽约客我还知道
l'm familiar with The New Yorker.
纽约客吗？ 对呀，纽约客嘛
'' The New Yorker? Yes, The New Yorker.'' Right?
可不是
That's right.
我想写一篇文章 报导你的遭遇...
l'm very interested in doing a piece on your situation here, and- -
是吗？是
Yeah? Yeah.
你要不要写上这个？
You wanna put this in?
我才不在乎他们要怎么判
l don't care what goes on here.
我没有错 就算到最高法院也是一样
l'm right, and l'll take it all the way to Supreme Court.
我才不管法官要怎么恶搞
Because that judge can screw herself.
- 这些话会照实写吗？ - 当然
- That for real would go in? - Absolutely.
我们从29号公路开场
We open on State Road 29.
一辆破烂白色旅行车 飞会开过来，向右急转...
A battered white van speeds along, making a sharp, skidding right...
来到法喀哈契浅滩 州立保育区
...into the Fakahatchee Strand State Preserve.
开车的是个没有门牙的瘦子
The driver of the van is a skinny man with no front teeth.
他就是老许
This is John Laroche.
我要休息一下
I need a break.
- 我喜欢西比流士小提琴协奏曲 - 我也喜欢，非常好听
- l loved the Sibelius violin concerto. - Yeah, me too. lt was great.
- 结尾有些诡异，但是... - 哎呀，不是啦，那是热情
- The end was a little weird, but... - Oh, no! God, it was passionate.
一种狂喜的心情
lt was exultant.
独奏部分棒极了 曲调优美精确无比
The soloist was amazing. Such beautiful tones. So precise.
天哪，简直令我疯狂
God, it blows my mind.
- 真希望我也能拉得那么好 - 你跟他一样好
- l wish l could play like that. - You do.
查理我没有那么好 不过是个泛泛之辈
Charlie. l don't. l'm mediocre at best.
至少我喜欢听你演奏
Well, l love listening to you play.
谢谢你，查理
Thanks, Charlie.
到家啦
Here we are.
接下来呢？
What are you up to now, then?
我该睡了 明天早上还有很多工作
l should probably get to bed. l have a lot of work to do tomorrow.
好吧，那就再见了
Well, good night, then.
我很想晚点回去
l would stay out.
实在是我的剧本 让我伤透脑筋
lt's just that l've really been struggling on the script right now.
我觉得好像太单薄 如果只是写一个老许的故事
l've been thinking about it too small, just writing it like a story about Laroche.
我是说，好像不够充实 我是要写花卉
That's not enough. l mean, l wanted to write about flowers.
总之，我想不出来 所以我最近睡不好...
Anyway, l can't figure it out, and l haven't been sleeping very well lately...
我想我应该回家...
...so l thought l should get home...
好好的睡一觉 这样早上才有精神
...and try to get a good night's sleep, you know. Start fresh in the morning.
不然，我可以不回去
Otherwise, l'd stay out.
我了解，我希望你理出头绪 查理，真的
l understand. l hope you figure it out, Charlie. l really do.
谢了 ，总之谢谢你跟我出来
Thanks. Thanks for coming out with me and everything.
不用客气，我玩得很开心
Sure, it was fun.
下周末我要去圣巴巴拉 有一场兰花大展
So l have to go to Santa Barbara next weekend for this orchid show up there.
希望你也一起去
l thought maybe you could come.
不了 ，我...
No, l....
下周末可能没空
l don't think l can make it next weekend.
应该不行
l don't think l can.
我另外有事，抱歉
l've got something. Sorry.
好吧
Okay.
好吧，那就只好算了 再见了
So, well, okay, then. So good night, then.
再见，查理
Good night, Charlie.
为什么不进去？ 我真窝囊
Why didn't I go in? I'm such a chicken.
我白痴，我应该吻她 我搞砸了
I'm such an idiot. I should have kissed her. I've blown it.
赶快再去敲门 然后吻她
I should just go and knock on her door right now and kiss her.
一定很罗曼蒂克 老了还可以和子孙吹嘘
It would be romantic. Something we could someday tell our kids.
我要立刻这样去做
I'm gonna do that right now.
3年前，佛罗里达 3年前，佛罗里达
- 谢谢你来接我 - 这辆车很破
- Thanks for picking me up. - This van's a piece of shit.
只要让我中了刮刮乐 我会买一部拉风好车
But when l hit the jackpot, l'll buy myself an awesome car.
你开的是什么车？
Hey, what are you driving?
那是...租来的
lt's... Well, it's a rental.
- 是一部鲁米那 - 好车
- lt's a Lumina. - Awesome.
我也要买一部那种车
l think l'll get one of those too.
出发了
Here we go.
瞧瞧这些驾驶的德性 是吧
Where do these people learn to drive, huh?
全世界都疯了
The world's insane.
我对你在园艺方面...
So l was impressed to hear...
的成就印象深刻
...how accomplished you are in the world of horticulture.
你必须要知道...
The thing you gotta know is...
我一生都千方百计 想要发财？
...my whole life is looking for a goddamn profitable plant, see?
我看中了鬼兰
And that's the ghost.
为什么要选鬼兰？
Why the ghost orchid?
一堆烂货 车里有怪味
因为她很稀有
Well, the sucker's rare. You know?
我是全世界 唯一懂得培养鬼兰的人
And l'm the only one in the world who knows how to cultivate it.
重点是要请印地安人 从沼泽地区采摘
See, the idea was, get the lndians to pull it from the swamp.
我研究过，只要我们不碰她 佛罗里达州就不能碰我们
l researched it. Long as l don't touch the plant, Florida can't touch us.
我以后不用偷摘 店里就可以现成卖花
And l stop future poaching by making the flowers readily available in stores.
我成了英雄，花也得救了...
l'm a hero, the flowers are saved...
老许和大自然都胜利了
...Laroche and nature win.
美丽的幻象
棒极了
Great.
你写下来了吗？
Did you get that last part?
写下来了
Yeah, l sure did.
兰花是世界上最性感的花
Orchids are the sexiest flowers on Earth.
兰花的英文是从 拉丁文orchis来的
The name orchid derives from the Latin orchis, which means testicle.
嗨，查理
Hey, Charles.
我把剧本丢给妈看
l pitched my screenplay to Mom.
不要说丢给
Don't say ''pitch.''
抱歉，总之她说...
Sorry. Anyway, she said it was...
那是沉默的羔羊遇上 变态杀人狂
...Silence of the Lambs meets Psycho.
你们俩也应该合作 听说妈的构局很神
Maybe you guys could collaborate. l hear Mom's really good with structure.
艾咪为什么都不来了？
So how come Amelia doesn't come around anymore?
你是不是玩弄了人家？
Did you put the moves on her or something?
塞米诺 苗圃
我找老许
l'm looking for John Laroche.
我在写一篇老许的文章 想来看他
l'm writing an article on John, and l stopped by.
- 希望能够看到他 - 约翰不在
- l hoped l could see him. - John's not here.
你跟他去过沼泽地 对不对？
Well, you were at the swamp with him, weren't you?
我在法院见过你 我认得你
l saw you at the courthouse, that's how l know.
我是马邱奥修拉
l'm Matthew Osceola.
苏丝欧琳，幸会
Susan Orlean. Nice to meet you.
也许我可以跟你谈
Maybe l could talk to you for a second.
我只是想找一些灵感...
l'm just trying to get a feel for the whole operation....
你的头发很美
You have very beautiful hair.
谢谢你这么说
Thank you very much.
我才刚...
Thank you. l just....
今早刚洗过头
l just washed it this morning.
我用了润丝精
l just used a new conditioner.
我能感受你的哀伤
l can see your sadness.
真可爱
lt's lovely.
哎呀，我只是累了 我就是这个毛病
Well, l'm just tired, that's all. That's my problem.
我们可不可以谈一会...
So maybe we could chat a little bit...
- 让我收集一些资料... - 我跟你没有什么好谈
- ...and l could get some background... - l'm not going to talk to you much.
不是对你个人
lt's not personal.
是我们印地安人的习惯
lt's the lndian way.
火箭兰
Angraecum sesquipedale.
美呆了
Beauty! God!
达尔文描写过这一种
Darwin wrote about this one.
查尔斯达尔文？写进化论的家伙？ 记得吗？
Charles Darwin? Evolution guy? Hello?
看那一路垂下的蜜腺
You see that nectary all the way down there?
达尔文推论...
Darwin hypothesized a moth...
有一种12英寸鼻管的蛾 来替她授花粉
...with a nose 1 2 inches long to pollinate it.
每个人都骂他神经
Everyone thought he was a loon.
当然，后来真的着找到了 12英寸鼻管的和蛾
Then, sure enough, they found this moth with a 1 2- inch proboscis.
- “Proboscis”是鼻管的意思 - 我知道这个字的意思
- ''Proboscis'' means nose, by the way. - l know what ''proboscis'' means.
我们不要偏离主题 又不是气死人比赛
Hey, let's not get off the subject. This isn't a pissing contest.
重点是 她奇妙之处...
The point is, what's so wonderful...
是每一种花 都和特定昆虫...
...is that every one of these flowers has a specific relationship...
有一定的关联才能传宗接代
...with the insect that pollinates it.
有些兰花 看起来就像昆虫
There's a certain orchid looks exactly like a certain insect.
于是昆虫被吸引过来...
So the insect is drawn to this flower...
像是分身，像是神交...
...its double, its soul mate...
除了亲热 什么都不想做
...and wants nothing more than to make love to it.
等到虫子飞走...
After the insect flies off...
又去盯上另一个神交伴侣 和她亲热，替她授粉
...it spots another soul- mate flower and makes love to it, thus pollinating it.
但是花和昆虫 谁也不会了解...
And neither the flower nor the insect will ever understand...
它们亲热的真正意义
...the significance of their lovemaking.
它们哪里想得到，小小的振动 使世界有了生命？
How could they know that because of their little dance, the world lives?
但事实就是如此
But it does.
只要照着天赋去做...
By simply doing what they're designed to do...
背后却有奇妙的意义存在
...something large and magnificent happens.
依这种角度来看 它们是在教导我们如何生活
In this sense, they show us how to live.
说明心情才是 唯一的晴两指标
How the only barometer you have is your heart.
只要找到你的正确目标 别让任何事情阻碍你
How when you spot your flower, you can't let anything get in your way.
他真有个性 门牙没有了
He's really quite a character. No front teeth.
- 好像一点都不在乎 - 为什么不去镶假牙呢？
- Doesn't seem to bother him at all. - Why doesn't he get them fixed?
简直孤傲不群 竟让每个人看到他的缺牙
lt seems almost sociopathic to make everybody look at that.
是啊，但他的嘴上功夫 真是了得呢，宝贝
Yeah, but he gives a great blowjob, honey.
其实他蛮迷人的
He is a fascinating character, though.
听起来像金矿呢，苏丝
Sounds like a gold mine, Sue.
未尝不可，可说不定呢 他...
lt could be. l don't know, you know? He's....
他跟他爸爸住 迷恋他亡母，而且...
He lives with his dad, he's obsessed with his dead mother, and....
老是把墨镜挂在脖子上
He wears his sunglasses on a little dingle- dangle around his neck.
爱得要死
Loving it.
- 说说他的车子 - 好啦，车子
- Tell them about the van. - Okay, the van. The van.
- 我现在不能说，我要去尿尿 - 不要，快说他的车子
- l can't tell about the van. l gotta pee. - No, tell us about the van.
- 简直妙极了 ，那是... - 里面有什么？
- lt's amazing. lt's.... - What's in it?
- 你们在车里做爱 - 闭嘴
- You did it in the van. - Shut up.
大卫你来说... 你不准说，不可以说
David, you tell... Don't you tell them. Don't tell them.
好吧，关于车子
Okay, the van.
大卫
David!
车子里面都是垃圾...
This van was filled with junk- -
闭嘴！
Shut up!
一罐罐泥土，铲子 食物包装纸，肥料
Potting soil. Shovels. Food wrappers. Fertilizer.
至少苏丝说 她宁可称它们是肥料
Susie said she hoped it was fertilizer, anyway.
其实她也不确定 老许也有他温馨的一面
She said she couldn't be sure. Laroche had a certain aromatic look about him.
据她说...
And she said- -
也许他的着迷程度 使他吃喝拉撒睡...
She said perhaps his obsessiveness didn't leave room in his schedule...
都在车上解决
...for personal hygiene.
也许兰花能供应 足够的水分
Maybe the orchids got all the available water.
我希望像人们喜爱兰花一样 的渴望一项事物
I wanted to want something as much as people wanted these plants.
但...
But...
我的个性不是这样
...it isn't part of my constitution.
我确实也有一桩 不怕被人讪笑的热情
I suppose I do have one unembarrassed passion.
我希望能亲身体会 付出全副心神热爱某事的感觉
I wanna know what it feels like to care about something passionately.
谁要是有幸见到鬼兰...
''Should one be lucky enough to see a ghost orchid...
其他花卉就会黯然失色
...all else will seem eclipsed. ''
如果鬼兰真是幽灵...
If the ghost orchid was really a phantom...
也是令人神魂颠倒的幽魂 引诱人们无止境的追寻...
...it was still such a bewitching one that it could seduce people to pursue it...
年复一年 忘却征途辛劳
...year after year and mile after miserable mile.
如果真有这种花 我一定要亲眼看看
If it was a real flower, I wanted to see one.
不是为了我爱兰花 我甚至根本不喜欢兰花
The reason was not that I love orchids. I don't even especially like orchids.
我只是希望亲眼目赌...
What I wanted was to see this thing...
人们更会被吸引迷恋 到如此强烈的钟情地步
...that people were drawn to in such a singular and powerful way.
那你总共收集了多少乌龟？
So how many turtles did you end up collecting?
我很会就没兴趣了
l lost interest right after that.
自从我爱上冰河时期的化石 我就放弃了乌龟
l dropped turtles when l fell in love with lce Age fossils.
没命的收集化石
Collected the shit out of them.
化石成为这个烂世界上 唯一有意义的东西
Fossils were the only thing that made sense to me in this fucked- up world.
我又放弃了化石 转向修复旧镜面水银
l ditched fossils for resilvering old mirrors.
我妈和我收集了一大堆...
My mom and l had the largest collection...
19世纪荷兰镜子
...of 1 9th- century Dutch mirrors on the planet.
你可能读过有关的报导 镜子世界，1988年10月？
Perhaps you read about us. Mirror World, October '88?
我还留了一份拷贝
l got a copy here somewhere.
我只是想知道 你是如何割舍...
l guess l'd just like to know how you can detach from something...
一件曾经投注全部心神的嗜好
...that you've invested so much of your soul in.
我是说，你从不怀念乌龟吗？
l mean, didn't you ever miss turtles?
那件在你10岁的时候 支持你活下去的东西？
The only thing that made your 1 0- year- old life worth living?
我告诉你一个故事好了？
Look, l'll tell you a story, all right?
我曾经死心塌地 的爱上热带鱼
l once fell deeply, you know, profoundly in love with tropical fish.
我家里有60座金鱼缸
l had 60 goddamn fish- tanks in my house.
我会去浮潜寻找喜爱的品种
l'd skin- dive to find just the right ones.
猪鱼，皇后天使鱼 四眼蝴蝶鱼
Anisotremus virginicus, Holacanthus ciliaris, Chaetodon capistratus.
应有尽有
You name it.
然后有一天我说“去他的鱼”
Then one day l say, ''Fuck fish.''
我屏弃了鱼 发誓不再涉足海洋
l renounce fish. l vow never to set foot in that ocean again.
全然把鱼否定
That's how much ''fuck fish.''
那是17年前的事 我再也没有碰过海
That was 1 7 years ago, and l have never since stuck a toe in that ocean.
但我是爱海的
And l love the ocean.
什么道理呢？
But why?
跟鱼了结了
Done with fish.
如果你真正喜欢某件事 难道不会有一丝丝怀念吗？
If you'd really loved something, wouldn't a little bit of it linger?
显然老许的了结 都是干净彻底
Evidently Laroche's finishes were downright and absolute.
头也不回一下
He just moved on.
有时 我也希望有这种能耐
I sometimes wished I could do the same.
午安 你想吃什么？
Good afternoon. So, what looks good today?
给我莱姆派
The key lime pie, please.
一小块就好
A small slice.
还有1杯咖啡 请加脱脂奶水
And a coffee, please. Skim milk, please.
兰花，我喜欢兰花
Orchids. l love orchids.
正点，这是...
Cool. That's....
你的派马上就来
Well, l'll be right back with your pie.
我好兴奋 我一向希望参观兰花大展
l'm so excited. l've always wanted to come to an orchid show.
我觉得这些花好性感
l think these flowers are so sexy.
我们到后面去瞧瞧
Let's see what's around back.
什么？
What?
- 要不要听听我的卖点？ - 走开，讨厌
- You wanna hear my pitch? - Go away, goddamn it.
我只是想找些事情做
You know, l'm just trying to do something.
谢了 ，伙伴，正点
Hey, thanks a lot, buddy. Cool.
有一个连续杀人犯，知道吗？
Okay, there's this serial killer, right?
等一下 警察要捉拿他
Well, no, wait. And he's being hunted by a cop.
而他却捉弄警察 透露下一次作案的线索
And he's taunting the cop, right? Sending clues who his next victim is.
他已经抓了一个人质
He's already holding her hostage in his creepy basement.
使得警察抓了狂 拼命想要找出人质的身份...
So the cop gets obsessed with figuring out her identity...
却在过程当中爱上了她
...and in the process falls in love with her.
虽然从来没有见过她 却好像成了...
Even though he's never even met her. She becomes like....
渴望得到的东西 就像圣杯
Like the unattainable. Like the Holy Grail.
- 这样不会太明显吗？ - 好吧，但是关键是这样的
- lt's a little obvious, don't you think? - Okay, but here's the twist.
我们发现杀人犯...
We find out that the killer...
其实是罹患了 多重人格分裂症
...really suffers from multiple personality disorder. Right?
其实杀人犯就是那个警察 也是那个女孩
See, he's actually really the cop and the girl.
所有的人都是他 是不是天下大乱了？
All of them are him. lsn't that fucked up?
多重人格和连续杀人犯 虽然都是老掉牙的题材
The only idea more overused than serial killers is multiple personality.
但我们可以藉此铺陈...
On top of that, you explore the notion...
警察和杀人犯 其实是一个人的两面
...that cop and criminal are really two aspects of the same person.
警察电影中 常看到这类的例子
See every cop movie ever made for other examples of this.
妈称之为心理上的错乱
Mom called it psychologically taut.
你有没有考虑过 根本无法写得出来？
The other thing is, there's no way to write this. Did you consider that?
你看，这么可能有人 被囚禁在地下室...
l mean, how could you have somebody held prisoner in a basement...
同时又能在警局上班？
...and working in a police station at the same time?
- 用摄影技巧 - 我不是问这个
- Trick photography. - Okay, that's not what l'm asking.
听仔细了 我要问的是
Listen closely. What l'm asking is:
这部电影当中 实际上只有一个角色对吗？
ln the reality of this movie, where there's only one character, right?
对吗？
Okay?
你怎么可能...？
How could you...?
为什么可以...？
What exactly would...?
我同意妈的说法，非常错乱
l agree with Mom. Very taut.
千面女碰上... 剃刀边缘
Sybil meets, l don't know.... Dressed to Kill.
真的，我很喜欢剃刀边缘
Cool. l really liked Dressed to Kill.
- 直到第3幕收场 - 不是这样发音
- Until the third act denouement. - That's not how it's pronounced.
抱歉，我... 好吧，对不起
Sorry. l... Okay, sorry.
- 又要来一点莱姆派吗？ - 可以，我喜欢
- Some key lime pie for you today? - Okay, yeah. That sounds great.
我会切一块大一点的 特别优待
l'll cut you an extra- large slice. Preferred customer.
- 谢谢你，你真好 - 我是个甜姐儿，对吗？
- Thank you. That's really sweet of you. - Well, l'm just a sweetie, ain't l?
- 你还有在研究兰花把？ - 是的，我有
- Still reading about orchids, l hope? - Yes, l am.
我有一个朋友 有1棵小小的粉红色的...
This friend of mine has this little, tiny pink one...
就像这样长在树枝上
...that grows on a tree branch just like that.
- 我想不起名字... - 这叫做附生
- l can't remember... - That's called an epiphyte.
对，对！
Right. Right!
你真不是盖的
Boy, you know your stuff.
没有啦，我正在学
No, not really. l'm just learning.
附生植物长在树上 但他们不是寄生
Epiphytes grow on trees, but they're not parasites.
他们的养分来自空气和两水
They get all their nourishment from the air and the rain.
真是令我大开眼界
Well, l'm impressed. That's great.
世上共有3万种兰花
There are more than 30,000 kinds of orchids in the world.
- 喔，可真多耶？ - 是啊
- Wow, that's a lot, huh? - Yeah. Yeah.
对
Yeah.
我马上就送大片莱姆派 给我的兰花专家
So l'll be right back with an extra- large slice of key lime pie for my orchid expert.
不过，我是在想...
But... So anyway, l was also wondering....
这个周末我要到圣芭芭拉 去看兰花大展，我...
l'm going up to Santa Barbara this Saturday for an orchid show, and l....
- 对不起 - 这个...
- l'm sorry. - Well....
- 我道歉，我不该 - 你的派马上就来
- l apologize. l'm sorry. - So l'll just be right back with your pie.
已知的兰花超过三万种
There are more than 30,000 known orchid species.
有的像乌龟
One looks like a turtle.
有的像猴子
One looks like a monkey.
有的像洋葱
One looks like an onion.
有的像老师
One looks like a schoolteacher.
有的像是体操选手
One looks like a gymnast.
有的像高中时候 皮肤细嫩的女同学
One looks like that girl in high school with creamy skin.
有的像纽约的知识份子...
One looks like a New York intellectual...
礼拜天在床上 玩纽约时报字谜游戏
...with whom you do the Sunday Times crossword puzzle in bed.
有的像中西部选美皇后
One looks like a Midwestern beauty queen.
也有像艾咪的
One looks like Amelia.
有的眼睛神采飞扬
One has eyes that dance.
有的眼光中带着哀伤
One has eyes that contain the sadness of the world.
于是我结婚了 我和我的美丽太太...
So l got married, and me and my beautiful new wife...
现在是前妻，那个婊子...
...my now ex- wife, the bitch...
开了一间苗圃
...opened up a nursery.
人们开始问我问题...
People started coming out of the woodwork to ask me stuff...
欣赏我种的花 也欣赏我
...and admire my plants and admire me.
我觉得有的人根本是因为寂寞 来找我做伴
l think some people were really spending time with me because they were lonely.
你知道我为什么喜欢植物？
And you know why l like plants?
因为它们随遇而安
Because they're so mutable.
能适应各种环境变迁
Adaptation's a profound process.
这意味着...
lt means you...
必须要设法求生存
...figure out how to thrive in the world.
对，但对植物比较容易 我是说...
Yeah, but it's easier for plants. l mean...
它们没有记忆
...they have no memory.
它们过一天算一天 但人类，如今...
You know, they just move on to whatever's next. But a person, now...
适应环境几乎变成可耻 我是说，就好像...
...adapting's almost shameful. l mean, it's like...
逃避
...running away.
基诺！
Keener!
嗨，老兄
Hey, man.
不要勾搭工作人员 ，唐诺
Please don't hit on crew members, Donald.
什么，那个化妆师吗？ 是她来勾引我，老哥
What, the makeup girl? She was hitting on me, bro.
别丢我的脸 我必须和他们共事
Don't embarrass me. l have to work with these people.
不会啦，我跟你说...
l won't. Anyway, listen...
我一直想问你 我需要一个杀人的好点子
...l meant to ask you, l need a cool way to kill people.
别担心，我要写剧本
Don't worry. For my script.
我不写那种东西
l don't write that kind of stuff.
拜托啦 你比较天才嘛
Come on, man, please? You're the genius.
这样吧 凶手是个文学教授
Here you go: The killer's a literature professor.
他把受害者肢解成小块小块
He cuts off little chunks from his victim's bodies until they die.
他自称为 “碎刀使者”
He calls himself ''The Deconstructionist.''
- 这点子不错，我喜欢 - 我是开玩笑的，唐诺
- That's kind of good. l like that. - See, l was kidding, Donald.
是喔，对不起
Okay. Sorry.
你唬到我了
You got me.
我要用的话，你不反对吧？
Do you mind if l use it, though?
- 其实很不错 - 我本来想把凯西的一幕...
- lt's really good. - l tried to split the Cassie scene in half...
- 从头到尾分成两半 - 我看到了 ，为什么要这样呢？
- ...from the beginning to the end. - l saw that. Why did you do that?
我要让气氛紧张起来 然后再会合起来...
Because l wanted there to be more tension. And then you pick it up later....
- 你改写了...？ - 营造紧张气氛
- But are you changing...? - Keeps more tension.
这样观众一开始 就被上紧发条
That way the audience gets stuck early on.
- 你喜欢吗？ - 我喜欢
- You like it? - l really like it.
你今晚好诱人，宝贝
You look hot tonight, baby.
谢了 ，唐诺 你嘴真甜
Thanks, Donald. That's swell of you to say.
- 她是不是很诱人，老哥？ - 我要回家了 ，唐诺
- Don't you think she's hot, bro? - l'm heading home, Donald.
是吗？别扫兴
Really? Come on.
嘿，艾咪来了
Hey, it's Amelia.
嗨，艾咪！
Hey, Amelia!
嗨，唐诺 嗨，查理
Hey, Donald. Hey, Charlie.
- 嗨，两位 - 艾咪，好久没看到你了
- Hey. Hi there. - God, Amelia, we don't see you anymore.
- 很高兴看到你 - 这位是我女朋友，凯莲
- lt's good to see you. - This is my girlfriend, Caroline.
- 她是电影化妆师 - 嗨
- She's a makeup artist for the movies. - Hi.
嗨
Hi.
这位是大卫，我朋友
This is David, my friend.
- 嗨 - 嘿，幸会
- Hi. - Hey. Nice to meet you.
- 艾咪常跟我提起你 - 嗨，我是唐诺
- Amelia's talked a lot about you. - Hi, l'm Donald.
- 嘿 - 凯莲
- Hey. - Caroline.
- 相机很酷 - 近来好吗？
- Cool camera. - So how are you?
- 你知道的，一塌糊涂 - 查理...
- You know me, a mess. - Charlie...
真的很高兴看到你 工作顺利吗？
...it's really good to see you. ls the work good?
一塌糊涂 我不知道我在做什么
lt's a disaster. l don't know what l'm doing.
总之，那是我自己的问题 别让我扫你的兴
But, anyway, it's my problem. l don't want to bore you.
你有你自己的事情 我是说，我们各自有各自的事情
You have your own stuff, right? l mean, we both have our own separate stuff.
总之，我得回去了 我正要回家工作
Anyway, l should go. l was just heading home to do some work.
- 你走不走？ - 不了 ，今晚我睡凯莲家
- You coming? - No, l'm gonna stay at Caroline's tonight.
在树业里推呀推呀推
A little push, push in the bush.
唐诺，你真糗！
Donald, you're such a tard!
再见，查理
See you, Charlie.
描写花卉 编写花的故事...
To write about a flower, to dramatize a flower...
一定要表现出花的弧度
...I have to show the flower's arc.
这个弧度一直弯曲到 生命的开端
And the flower's arc stretches back to the beginning of life.
花究竟怎么来的？ 它有过哪些遭遇？
How did this flower get here? What was its journey?
因此 我必须引用类比推论法...
Therefore, I should infer from analogy...
英格兰，一百三十九年前
可能地球上所有 有机体的生长...
...that probably all the organic beings which have ever lived on this Earth...
都是来自同一种原生型态...
...have descended from some one primordial form...
衍化成第一种会呼吸的生命
...into which life was first breathed.
这是一种进化过程 适者生存
It is a journey of evolution. Adaptation.
我们都经历过的 把我们全体结合在一起的过程...
The journey we all take. A journey that unites each and every one of us.
达尔文认为我们都是 从同一种单细胞演化
Darwin writes that we all come from the very first single- cell organism.
然而我是我
Yet here I am.
老许是老许 还有欧琳
And there's Laroche. There's Orlean.
还有鬼兰 陷在各自的躯体之中...
And there's the ghost orchid. All trapped in our own bodies...
分别存在历史时空某一点上 就是如此
...in moments in history. That's it.
我所要做的 是把所有历史串联起来
That's what I need to do. Tie all of history together.
远从地球上生命的起端
Start right before life begins on the planet.
当时一切...
All is...
了无生息 然后，生命开始...
...lifeless. And then, like, life begins...
生成有机体 就是那些单细胞生物
...with organisms. Those little single- cell ones.
性生活还没开始 因为好像，一切都是无性的
And it's before sex, because, like, everything was asexual.
后来演化出较大生物 水母
From there we go to bigger things. Jellyfish.
后来又有长脚的鱼 爬上了陆地
Then that fish that got legs and crawled out on the land.
于是出现了恐龙
And then we see, you know, like, dinosaurs.
恐龙经历一段很长年代 然后一颗流星带来了 ：
And then they're around for a long time. Then an asteroid comes and:
...昆虫、哺乳类、灵长类、猿猴
...the insects, the mammals, the primates, monkeys.
单纯的猴子 渐渐出现新的品种
The simple monkeys. Old- fashioned monkeys giving way to the new ones.
诸如，猩猩出现 诸如，然后人类
Whatever. And then apes. Whatever. And man.
接着就是人类文明的历史 狩猎、战争、情爱...
Then we see the whole history of human civilization: hunting, war, love...
心痛、疾病、孤寂、科技
...heartache, disease, loneliness, technology.
最后来到苏丝欧琳 在纽约客的办公室...
And we end with Susan Orlean in her office at The New Yorker...
她正在写花卉报导！ 于是乎，电影开场
...writing about flowers, and bang! The movie begins.
这正是我期待的突破 之前未曾做到过
This is the breakthrough I've been hoping for. It's never been done.
马契真是天才！
McKee is a genius!
而且风趣，他的笑话总是引得 大家哈哈大笑
And hilarious. He just comes up with all these great jokes, and everybody laughs.
但他也很严谨，查理 你会喜欢他的
But he's serious too, Charles. You'd love him.
他的灵感新颖丰富，和你一样
He's all for originality, just like you.
但他说 我们必须依照类型来写...
But he says we have to realize that we all write in a genre...
要在类型之中寻求创意
...and we must find our originality within that genre.
劳勃马契的编剧研讨班
费里尼首创仿记录片类型之前 从来没出现过新的类型
There hasn't been a new genre since Fellini invented the mockumentary.
我的类型是恐怖片 ，你的呢？
My genre's thriller. What's yours?
我们的遗传基因相同
You and l share the same DNA.
还有什么比这更孤单呢？
ls there anything more lonely than that?
你说啥，老哥？
What'd you say, bro?
- 是吗？ - 嘿
- Yeah? - Hey.
嘿，苏丝Q
Hey, Susie- Q.
你有什么企图？
What you up to?
我不会太打扰你 我只想来见你， 多找些材料
l don't wanna bother you. Just thought l'd call and get some more info.
你为何不说些有智慧的话
I think you say some pretty smart things, John.
是啊，所见过最聪明的家伙？
Yeah, smartest guy l know, huh?
那么...
So...
你的苗圃究竟出了什么事？
...whatever happened to your nursery?
本来一切都很顺利
lt was going pretty well.
只是，天有不测风云 黑暗降临
But, you know, sometimes bad things happen, darkness descends.
九年前，北迈阿密
苗圃生意好吗，约翰？
Nursery business good, Johnny?
万事顺利，金叔
Everything's good, Uncle Jim.
最近这一年好得出奇
This last year's been a dream.
跟你说 我们终于转亏为盈了
l'm telling you. Finally pulling out of debt.
阿门，亲爱的 我真以你为荣...
Amen, honey. l'm so proud of you two, and- -
不，我真抱歉 我不知道
No, ma'am. l'm sorry, l can't answer that.
- 不要动 - 嘿
- Stay right there. - Hey.
- 等一下，是谁死了？ - 拜托你不要乱动
- Hold it. Which ones are dead? - Sir, please, don't move.
- 死了哪些人？ - 动身了 ！
- Which ones are dead? - Let's move it!
我害死我妈和叔叔
I killed my mom, you know, and my uncle.
门牙也是那样掉的
That's how I lost my front teeth.
我老婆昏迷了 大约三个星期
And my wife was in a coma for, like, three weeks.
一清醒就和我离了婚
And she divorced me soon after she regained consciousness.
我想，如果差点死掉的是我 我也会想要离婚
Well, l think if l almost died, l would leave my marriage too.
为什么呢？
Why?
因为我可以
Because l could.
就像是张免费票 没有人可以批判...
Because it's like a free pass. Nobody can judge you...
如果你差点死去
...if you almost died.
可是，我就批判了她
Well, l judged her.
也许我也受到了批判
Maybe l was being judged too.
没过一个月 安德鲁飓风来袭
It was like a month after that, Hurricane Andrew came along and just...
好像老天派来的密使 一扑而下
...swooped down like an angel of God...
卷走了我所剩的一切
...and just wiped out everything I had left.
一切所有
Everything.
我不忍心重新经营苗圃...
I knew it'd break my heart to start another nursery...
所以 当塞米诺人找上我...
...so, you know, when the Seminoles called...
他们要找个专家白人 帮忙经营苗圃 ，我就答应了
...they wanted a white guy or an expert to get their nursery going, l took the job.
我不是要帮他们经营 传统式一盆盆的花草
l wasn't gonna give them a conventional little potted- plant place.
我要给他们一些...
l was gonna give them something...
奇特的东西，你懂吗？
...amazing, you know?
我了解
Yeah, I know, John.
我知道
I know.
我准备给他们一些神奇的
''l was going to give them something amazing.''
兰花痴 苏丝欧琳着
写得真美 你的见解独到
lt's beautifully written. You have such a unique voice.
谢谢
Thank you very much.
- 我们是你的忠实书迷 - 谢谢
- We're big fans. - Thank you.
老许的角色真有趣
Laroche is such a fun character.
- 是啊 - 有趣而且新鲜
- Yeah. - lt's funny and fresh.
也带着点感伤
And sad in a way.
不知道你下一篇要写什么
So we were wondering what's next.
兰登屋来找我接洽过...
Well, Random House has asked me...
想把它扩展成书 我会忙于此事
...to expand it into a book, so l'm gonna be doing that.
- 而且... - 苏丝，我们想要买断
- And... - Susan, we would like to option this.
- 你们要改编成电影？ - 拍电影
- You wanna make it into a movie? - lnto a movie.
噢，天那！
Oh, God!
- 真的太... - 你觉得如何？
- That's really.... - How does that sound?
- 叫人兴奋 - 很好
- That's very exciting. - Good.
有点滑稽，我不曾思考过 我没有编剧过
lt's just comical. l hadn't thought of it. l've never written a screenplay before.
这不用你担心 我们有编剧会负责
Don't worry about that. We have screenwriters to write the screenplay.
嘿，超级巨星 我是马帝，超级代理人
Hey, superstar. It's Marty, super agent.
我只是提醒你 已经13个礼拜了...
I just wanna remind you it's been 1 3 weeks...
薇拉急着想看剧本
...and Valerie's anxious to see a draft.
请你务必在礼拜一送去给她
So if you could wrap things up and get it to her by Monday, that'd be great.
听到留言回我电话 拜拜，朋友
Call me when you get this. Adios, amigo.
兰花贼 查理考夫曼编剧
你笑什么？
What? What'd you laugh at?
- 你真天才 - 哪一句？
- You're a genius. - Which line?
你真天才 你真天才
You're a genius. You're a genius.
我们看到兰花大盗 奥古斯塔马加里
''We see orchid hunter Augustus Margary.
额头绑着一条肮脏破布 用来减轻头痛
He wears a filthy, spittle- soaked rag around his head to quell the pain.
裤子后面沾满排泄物...
The back of his trousers are stained greasy black from an anal leakage...
因为得了痢疾
...due to dysentery.
他在浓密的业林中呻吟 举步维艰
He moans with each tentative step through the overgrown jungle. ''
我受不了了
I'm fucked.
我们从老许开场 他幽默的说“我喜欢让花草变种”
We open with Laroche. He's funny. He says, ''I love to mutate plants. ''
他说“变种很好玩” 我们展出花卉
He says, ''Mutation is fun. '' Okay, we show flowers and.... Okay.
我们要用法庭的案子 我们展现老许
We have to have the court case. We show Laroche.
他说“我在婴儿时期就被变种了 我才会这么聪明”
He says, ''I was mutated as a baby. That's why I'm so smart. ''
很好笑 好吧，我们用混沌初开，不！
That's funny. Okay, we open at the beginning of time. No!
- 老许开车进入沼泽 - 疯狂白人！
- Laroche is driving into the swamp. - Crazy white man!
我不知道怎么改编它 我应该坚持用自己的素材
l don't know how to adapt this. l should have stuck with my own stuff.
我不知道为何 会以为我能改编它
l don't know why l thought l could write this.
看那女的？
See her?
我从后面玩过
l fucked her up the ass.
我说笑的
No. l'm kidding.
或许我能帮忙
Maybe l can help.
这是关于花卉
lt's about flowers.
好吧
Okay.
但不是只有花卉？ 其中还有个植物痴狂？
But it's not only about flowers, right? You have the crazy plant- nut guy, right?
他很滑稽，对吗？
He's funny. Right?
“他的事情根本不配写书”
''There's not nearly enough of him to fill a book.''
于是欧琳“旁敲侧击” 写了一堆废话
So Orlean ''digresses in long passages.'' Blah, blah, blah.
“支离破碎的拼凑” 纽约时报书评
''No narrative unites these passages.'' New York Times Book Review.
我无法组织它们 这种纽约客的烂类型
l can't structure this. lt's that sprawling New Yorker shit.
我该玩过她的后庭
Man, l'd fuck her up the ass.
- 抱歉 - 这本书没有剧情，毫无剧情
- Sorry. - The book has no story. There's no story.
好吧，那就捏造剧情
All right. Make one up.
我是说，城里只有你 最能写出脍炙人口的故事
l mean, nobody in this town can make up a crazy story like you.
- 你是个中翘楚 - 不，这回我不干
- You're the king of that. - No, l didn't want to do that this time.
这是别人的素材 我对苏丝要负责任的...
lt's someone else's material. l have a responsibility to Susan- -
总之，我要做个有长进的作家 我要写些单纯的
Anyway, l wanted to grow as a writer. l wanted to do something simple.
让观众理解花卉的迷人
Show people how amazing flowers are.
它们迷人吗？
Are they amazing?
我不知道，我想是吧
l don't know. l think they are.
- 你要帮我解套 - 好吧
- l need you to get me out of this. - All right.
查理，你已经整理好几个月了
Charlie, you've been stringing them along for months now.
现在还拿不出东西 恐怕不好看吧
Not to give them anything at this point would be a terrible career move.
嘿，我的剧本进行的很好
Hey, my script's going amazing.
现在 我使用一套影像系统
Right now, l'm working out an image system.
因为我的多重人格主题 我选了一个主题...
Because of my multiple personality theme, l've chosen a motif...
嘿，我的剧本进行的很好
Hey, my script's going amazing.
现在 我使用一套影像系统
Right now, l'm working out an image system.
因为我的多重人格主题 我选了一个主题...
Because of my multiple personality theme, l've chosen a motif...
用破碎的镜子 显示主角的分裂人格
...of broken mirrors to show my protagonist's fragmented self.
包勃说话影像系统 可以增加感官的复杂美感
Bob says an image system increases the complexity of an aesthetic emotion.
- 包勃说... - 你听起来简直像在虔诚膜拜
- Bob says... - You sound like you're in a cult.
不，那只是写作的技巧
No, it's just good writing technique.
我把马契的十大守则印了复本
l made you a copy of McKee's 1 0 Commandments.
在你我书桌前各贴了一份
l posted one over both our work areas.
劳勃马契的十大守则
你不该这样做
You shouldn't have done that.
那真的很有帮助 查理，我加了一首歌
Because it's extremely helpful. Hey, Charles, l'm putting a song on.
“快乐时光”
''Happy Together.''
大家穿着睡衣唱歌跳舞
Like when characters sing songs in their pajamas and dance around.
这样可以打破紧张气氛
l thought it'd break the tension.
刚开始我有些犹豫 在恐怖片中穿插歌曲...
At first l was nervous about putting a song in a thriller...
但包勃说北非谍影 有史以来最棒的剧本...
...but Bob says that Casablanca, one of the greatest screenplays ever written...
就这样做过 混合类型
...did exactly that. Mixed genres.
我已经一星期没睡了，唐诺
l haven't slept in a week, Donald.
- 我必须要睡觉 - 好吧
- l need to go to bed. - Okay.
晚安
Good night.
- 什么事？ - 嗨
- Yeah? - Hi.
老许，又是我啦
John, it's Susan again.
嘿，苏丝Q
Hey, Susie- Q.
进行得如何？
How's it going?
很好啊，我在训练网路技巧
Great. l'm training myself on the lnternet.
真是太神奇了 我在经营色情网站
lt's fascinating. l'm doing pornography.
我搞不懂这些痞子 为了马子照片愿意付多少钱
lt's amazing how much these suckers will pay for photographs of chicks.
不管她们是肥是丑
lt doesn't matter if they're fat or ugly or what.
听起来不错啊
Well, that sounds good.
很好呢，很真实
lt's great, is what it is.
我实在不愿多麻烦你 可是...
Listen, John, l hate feeling like l'm being a pain to you, but l....
我还没见过鬼兰
l still haven't seen a ghost.
- 是吗？ - 我希望你能带我...
- Yeah? - And I was hoping maybe you'd....
好啊
Yeah.
好，我来接你
Yeah, l'll take you in.
- 明天 - 真的？
- Tomorrow. - Really?
太谢谢你了
Thank you so much.
噢，老许
Oh, John.
可恶
Damn it.
有太多思绪事物和人物
There are too many ideas and things and people.
太多可以遵循的方向
Too many directions to go.
我开始渐渐觉得 真的需要特别关注一些事情...
I was starting to believe the reason it matters to care about something...
就可以把世界缩得小一点...
...is that it whittles the world down...
变得容易应付些
...to a more manageable size.
真是窝心，洞悉忧愁
Such sweet, sad insights.
那么真实
So true.
我喜欢看着你
l like looking at you.
我也喜欢看着你，查理
I like looking at you too, Charlie.
我不知道怎么继续下去
l don't know how to do this.
我怕会让你失望
l'm afraid l'll disappoint you.
你的书写得很美
You've written a beautiful book.
我睡不着
l can't sleep.
我在掉头发 又肥，又惹人厌
l'm losing my hair. l'm fat and repulsive.
嘘，你不会惹人厌
Shh. You're not. You're not.
把它简化一点？
Just whittle it down, you know?
把焦点放在故事面
Focus on one thing in the story.
找出那一件最最...
Find that one thing...
让你热中喜爱的事情
...that you care passionately about...
把它写出来
...and then write about that.
我们对苏丝欧琳的了解是 雅致的，被孤独所包围...
We see Susan Orlean: delicate, haunted by loneliness...
娇弱，而美丽
...fragile, beautiful.
躺在熟睡的粗俗丈夫身边 她醒着
She lies awake next to her sleeping, insensitive husband.
她开始旁白：
Her voice- over begins:
“我想我的确有一项 不怕被人知道的热衷”
''l suppose l do have one unembarrassed passion.
“我希望能亲身体会 付出全副心神热爱某事的感觉”
l want to know how it feels to care about something passionately.''
- 嘿 - 早啊
- Hey. - Morning.
两位早，改成早起啦？
Hey, you two. Up early for a change?
- 你精神好多了 - 我很好，我有了新点子
- You seem chipper. - l'm good. l have some new ideas.
你们俩真是聪明过人 这里简直就是智囊工厂
God, you guys are so smart. lt's like a brain factory in here.
- 今早我也有了新点子 - 他的新点子真的很棒很棒
- l got some ideas too this morning. - He got really, really good ones.
你知道，唐诺式的
You know, in a Donald sort of way.
我要加... 嘿！什么？
l'm putting... Hey! What?
我要增加一段追逐的戏 杀手...
l'm putting in a chase sequence. So the killer...
骑马带着女孩逃走 警察骑摩托车追赶
...flees on horseback with the girl. The cop's after them on a motorcycle.
就像是机器和马匹的战争
And it's like a battle between motors and horses.
科技对自然
Like technology versus horse.
那他们也还都是同一个人？
And they're still all one person, right?
啊呀，那是最大的代价
Well, that's the big payoff.
- 听起来很刺激 - 谢了，老兄
- lt sounds exciting. - Thanks, man.
- 谢谢 - 看吧，我说他一定会喜欢
- Thanks. - See, l told you he was gonna like it.
- 你是我的灵感女神，真的 - 我喜欢当你的缪斯
- You're my muse. You are. - l love being your muse.
我太高兴了
l'm so happy about that.
我来替考夫曼取件
l'm picking up an order for Kaufman.
- 薇拉 - 嗨，查理
- Valerie. - Hi, Charlie.
真巧啊 刚好碰到你
lt's quite a coincidence bumping into you.
抱歉我没有回你电话 上礼拜我不在
l'm sorry l didn't call you back. l was away last week.
- 没关系 - 本来要打的...
- That's okay. - l meant to because...
因为情况顺利多了 我想让你知道
...things are going really well now, and l wanted you to know.
那太好了 我很想看些成果
Well, that's great. l'm anxious to see something.
跟我们坐一下 我正在和苏丝吃饭
You should sit down because l'm here with Susan right now.
她好想见见你 碰到你真太巧了
And she's dying to meet you, so it's funny bumping into you.
- 来坐一下 - 苏丝欧琳也在这里？
- Have a seat. - Susan Orlean is here?
是啊，她正来城里有事 她正在打电话
Yeah, she's here in town for a reading or something. She's just on the phone.
坐一下嘛 她好想见你
Sit down. Have a seat. She's dying to meet you.
我还是走吧...
Well, l should probably go, because....
其实我也很想见她
Well, l'd love to meet her too...
但我不想欠她情 而且...
...but l don't want to be beholden. And, well- -
一旦见过你正在描写的人
Because once you meet somebody that you've been writing about...
就会失去客观判断...
...it becomes very hard to separate. So....
好了，我改天再和你联络 我快写好了
Well, okay, l'll speak to you soon. And l'm almost done.
就快好了
l'm almost done.
跟苏丝说我很乐意 在以后和她见面
And tell Susan that l would love to meet with her at a future date.
- 只要她方便 - 好吧
- As she sees fit. - Okay.
我在骗谁啊？ 这又不是在写苏丝欧琳
Who am I kidding? This is not Susan Orlean's story.
跟她毫无瓜葛 我却不敢见她
I have no connection with her. I can't even meet her.
除了自乱阵脚和自我憎恨以外 我啥也不懂...
I have no understanding of anything but my own panic and self- loathing...
还有可悲和小家子气
...and pathetic, little existence.
我只够格写我自己 只能写自己...
The only thing I'm actually qualified to write about is myself and my own self- -
查理考夫曼上场
We open on Charlie Kaufman.
肥胖的秃老，面目可憎 坐在好莱坞的一家餐厅...
Fat, old, bald, repulsive, sitting in a Hollywood restaurant...
面对着薇拉汤玛丝 端庄美丽的执行制作
...across from Valerie Thomas, a lovely, statuesque film executive.
考夫曼想要争取一件 编剧工作...
Kaufman, trying to get a writing assignment...
黄汗直冒地设法博取她的好感
...wanting to impress her, sweats profusely.
秃肥的考夫曼在卧室 气急败坏的踟躇着
Fat, bald Kaufman paces furiously in his bedroom.
对着手提录音机 说道：
He speaks into his hand- held tape recorder, and he says:
查理考夫曼 肥胖的秃老，面目可憎...
''Charlie Kaufman, fat, bald, repulsive, old...
“和薇拉汤玛丝 坐在老莱坞一家餐厅”
...sits at a Hollywood restaurant with Valerie Thomas.''
考夫曼，貌不登样，滑稽...
Kaufman, repugnant, ridiculous...
对着苏丝的书皮照片 打着手枪...
...jerks off to the book jacket photo of Susan Or- -
什么事？
What do you want?
我的剧本写好了
l've finished my script.
我完工了
l'm done.
可以请你的经纪人看吗？
So would you show it to your agent?
名叫“3”
lt's called The Three.
谢了 也要谢谢你的点子
Thanks. l also want to thank you for your idea.
帮了大忙 我稍微修改了
lt was very helpful. l changed it a little.
改成凶手强迫受害人 吃掉从身上切下的肉
Now the killer cuts off body pieces and makes his victims eat them.
凯琳有个蛇的刺青 吞食着自己的尾巴...
Caroline has this great tattoo of a snake swallowing its own tail, and- -
- 饿伯蛇 - 我不懂它的意思
- Ourobouros. - l don't know what that means.
那条蛇，叫做饿伯蛇
The snake. lt's called Ourobouros.
我不知道 但我凶手的“工法”真酷...
l don't think so. But it's cool for my killer to have this modus operandi...
他强迫那女人吃她自己的肉 而那女人其实是他自己...
...because when he forces the woman who's really him to eat herself...
他是在自己咬死自己
...he's also eating himself to death.
我疯了
l'm insane.
- 我是饿伯蛇 - 我不懂那个字的意思
- l'm Ourobouros. - l don't know what that word means.
- 我把自己写进剧本了 - 那样有点诡异吧？
- l've written myself into my screenplay. - That's kind of weird, huh?
这是自我放纵，是一种自我陶醉
lt's self- indulgent. lt's narcissistic.
那是唯我论，那是可悲
lt's solipsistic. lt's pathetic.
我真可悲 我又肥又可悲
l'm pathetic. l'm fat and pathetic.
你一定有你的道理，查理 你是艺术家
l'm sure you had good reasons, Charles. You're an artist.
是因为我太窝囊 不敢面对写那本书的女人
lt's because l'm too timid to speak to the woman who wrote the book.
因为我可悲
Because l'm pathetic.
因为我写不出来 因为我种不出美丽的花
Because l have no idea how to write. Because l can't make flowers fascinating.
因为我烂
Because l suck.
- 嘿，有没有写我啊？ - 我要去纽约
- Hey, am l in the script? - l'm going to New York.
我去见她，我决定了 我必须这样做
l'll meet her. That's it. That's what l have to do.
你可别生气...
Don't get mad at me for saying this...
但这个周末 劳勃正好在纽约办讲习
...but Bob's having a seminar in New York this weekend.
如果你写不下去...
So if you're stuck....
她说“老许真是滑稽” 她说“老许真是滑稽”
And she said, ''Laroche is such a fun character.'' And she said, ''Laroche is such a fun character.''
不是盖的，我是滑稽角色
No shit, l'm a fun character.
谁来演我？
Who's gonna play me?
我得先写完书
Well, l've gotta write the book first, John.
然后他们会找人编剧
Then, you know, they get somebody to write the screenplay.
嘿，我觉得应该由我来演自己
Hey, l think l should play me.
多数人渴望卓越事物 渴望心灵的启发...
Most people yearn for something exceptional, something so inspiring...
愿意为热情牺牲一切 一点都不作做
...that they'd want to risk everything for that passion, but few would act on it.
是一种强烈的力量...
It was very powerful...
和这种生意昂然的人相处 简直令人陶醉
...and it's intoxicating to be around someone so alive.
跟着我来吧 就在不远
Come on, just follow me. They're right nearby.
好
Okay.
我可以问个私人问题吗？
Can l ask you a personal question?
放心，我们没有迷路
Look, we're not lost.
我来过千百次了
l've done this a million times.
凡事不顺的时候我就说 “去它的” ，然后继续努力
When everything is killing me, l just say, ''Screw it,'' and go straight ahead.
噢，糟了...
Oh, fuck....
日晷
Sundial.
我把它竖起来 等上几分钟...
l'll just set this up, we'll wait a few minutes...
就可以知道 太阳移动的方向
...and then we'll be able to tell which way the sun's moving.
我们应该向东南方走
We should be headed southeast.
你也收集东西吗？
So, you collect anything?
也不尽然
Not really, no.
是啊，你知道...
Yeah, well, you know...
其实不是为了收集东西
...it's not really about collecting the thing.
而是想要去完成...
lt's about being able....
就像对电脑 我所喜欢的...
The thing about computers, the thing l like...
是能沉浸其中
...is that l'm immersed in them...
而它们没有生命 不会死去或别离
...but it's not like a living thing that's gonna leave or die or something.
- 对不起，我只是... - 没事
- John, l'm sorry. l just... - Okay.
- 我不是... - 嘿，没事
- l don't... - Hey. Okay.
去它的日晷
Fuck the sundial.
我知道怎么走出去 我知道怎么走出去
l know how to get out of here. l know how to get out of here.
这个泥淖 我早就了若指掌
l know this swamp like the back of my goddamn hand.
你和别人一模一样 吸血水蛭
You're just like everybody else. Fucking leeches.
尽管扒在我身上 吸干我的血，再吐掉
You just attach yourself to me and suck me dry, spit me out.
为什么不去过你自己的日子？ 把玩你自己的喜好？
Why don't you get your own fucking life? Your own fucking interests?
养尊处优的臭婆娘
Fucking spoiled bitch.
人生似乎充满了 类似鬼兰的事物
Life seemed to be filled with things that were just like the ghost orchid.
美好的憧憬 轻易的产生感情...
Wonderful to imagine and easy to fall in love with...
但却趋于幻想...
...but a little fantastic...
而且稍纵即逝...
...and fleeting...
难以捉摸
...and out of reach.
三年后
“...但却趋于幻想 稍纵即逝，而且难以捉摸”
''...but a little fantastic and fleeting and out of reach.''
魅力
纽约客
喂？
Hello?
嘿，我是马帝，进行得如何？
Hey, it's Marty. How's it going?
和原作者谈过有帮助吗？ 她叫什么来的？
Has it been helpful talking to the writer? What's her name?
苏丝欧琳，很顺利
Susan Orlean. It's been okay.
我是说有没有什么进展？
Well, l mean, are you making headway?
薇拉逼得我喘不过气
Valerie's breathing down my neck.
- 灵感不能催逼 - 好吧好吧，算你有理
- You can't rush inspiration. - Okay. All right. Fair enough.
我打电话的另一理由 是关于“3”
Listen, the other reason l called was The Three.
简直棒极了
lt's just amazing.
- 我不知道那是什么 - 唐诺的剧本啊
- l don't know what that is. - Donald's script.
一部慧诘、锐利的恐怖片 是我今年读到最棒的剧本
A smart, edgy thriller. It's the best script I've read all year.
- 很好 - 是啊，我要卖它个好价钱
- Good. - Yeah, I'm gonna sell it for a shitload.
一家出两个才子
Two fucking talented guys in one family.
其实，何不让你老弟 在兰花上助你一臂之力
In fact, maybe you could get your brother to help you with the orchid thing.
- 马帝，别这样说，我是说... - 好吧，只是想想而已，老兄
- Marty, don't say that. l mean... - All right. It's just a thought, buddy.
我是说 他的组织力真是好
I mean, he's really goddamn amazing at structure.
- 我得挂断了 - 好的，别了，朋友
- l have to go. - All right. Adios, amigo.
赶快完成它...
Finish that- -
可恶！
Fuck!
劳勃马契 编剧讲习班
好，谢谢
Okay, thank you, thank you.
接着有漫长的三天
We have a long three days ahead.
几年后，你们将会在 华丽的酒会上沾沾自喜...
Years from now, you'll be at a posh cocktail party congratulating yourself...
庆幸有个好莱坞痞子 和你共渡了这个周末
...on how you spent a weekend with an asshole from Hollywood for your art.
- 我真可悲，我是失败者 - 那么...
- I am pathetic. I am a loser. - So...
写作的真义是什么？
...what is the substance of writing?
我失败了，我慌张了 我已经江郎才尽，一无是处
I have failed. I am panicked. I have sold out. I am worthless.
我...还在这里干嘛？
I... What the fuck am I doing here?
我在这里干嘛？真是的
What the fuck am I doing here? Fuck!
这正是我的缺点 我毫无主见的来到这里
It is my weakness, my ultimate lack of conviction that brings me here.
走捷径 让你能一步登天
Easy answers, rules to shortcut yourself to success.
我会来这里是因为 我介入这一行却毫无所获
And here I am because my jaunt into the abyss brought me nothing.
这不是想要追求新鲜事物 都必须承担风险？
Well, isn't that just the risk one takes for attempting something new?
我应该马上回去 我要从头做起，面对我的任务...
I should leave right now. I'll start over. I need to face this project head- on- -
如果你要使用旁白 就只有老天爷能帮助你了
And God help you if you use voice- over in your work, my friends.
老天保佑 那是最草率、最松散的写法
God help you. lt's flaccid, sloppy writing.
哪个白痴也会使用旁白叙述 来说明角色的思想
Any idiot can write voice- over narration to explain the thoughts of the character.
好吧，先讲到这里 午餐休息一小时
Okay, that's it. One hour for lunch.
引领故事发展的主角 不能没有情欲需求
You cannot have a protagonist without desire.
否则就说不出一个道理 毫无道理
It doesn't make any sense. Any fucking sense.
大家了解吗？很好
You follow? Good.
谁还有问题？
Anyone else?
如果故事内容很少 编剧应该如何铺陈？
What if a writer is attempting to create a story where nothing much happens?
如果人不会改变 就不会产生顿悟
Where people don't change, they don't have any epiphanies.
他们挣扎、挫败 却一事无成
They struggle and are frustrated, and nothing is resolved.
这是真实世界的写照
More a reflection of the real world.
真实世界吗？
The real world?
对了，先生
Yes, sir.
就是这个真实世界
The real fucking world.
首先，如果你写的剧本 没有冲突和危机...
First of all, you write a screenplay without conflict or crisis...
你会让观众无聊到掉泪
...you'll bore your audience to tears.
其次，世上没有事情发生？
Secondly, nothing happens in the world?
你是不是脑筋打铁了？
Are you out of your fucking mind?
每天有人被谋杀
People are murdered every day.
有种族灭绝、战争、贪污
There's genocide, war, corruption.
一天又一天 在世界各个角落...
Every fucking day, somewhere in the world...
有人牺牲生命去救别人
...somebody sacrifices his life to save somebody else.
每天每天 会有神智清明的人决定...
Every fucking day, someone somewhere takes a conscious decision...
去毁掉另一个人
...to destroy someone else.
有人找到爱情，有人失恋
People find love. People lose it.
天哪，孩子眼睁睁 看着母亲在教堂石阶被打死
Christ, a child watches a mother beaten to death on the steps of a church.
有人捱饿
Someone goes hungry.
有人为了女色背弃好友
Somebody else betrays his best friend for a woman.
如果你还找不到人生题材...
lf you can't find that stuff in life...
那你对生命 真是一无所知
...then you, my friend, don't know crap about life!
为什么还来浪费我的宝贵时间 讨论你的电影？
And why the fuck are you wasting my two precious hours with your movie?
我对你一点帮助都没有！
l don't have any use for it!
我一丁点都没有帮助！
l don't have any bloody use for it!
好，谢谢
Okay, thanks.
- 谢谢你 - 甭客气
- Thank you. - You're welcome.
不，谢谢你
No. Thank you.
太感谢你了，马契先生
Thank you so much, Mr. McKee.
这课程让人 重新以不同的角度看待写作
This course makes you look at writing in a whole different way.
- 马契先生 - 是？
- Mr. McKee. - Yes?
我是早上被你吼的人
l'm the guy you yelled at this morning.
我没听懂
l need more.
我是那个以为 人生无事的人
l'm the one who thought things didn't happen in life.
对了，好吧
Right. Okay.
- 很高兴认识你 - 我需要谈谈
- Nice to see you. - l need to talk.
马契先生，我会站在这里 已经够吓人的
Mr. McKee, my even standing here is very scary.
我通常不擅与人交往
l don't meet people well.
但早上你说的话 震撼到我的骨子里
But what you said this morning shook me to the bone.
你所讲的 不只是如何写作剧本而已
What you said was bigger than my screenwriting choices.
而是有关如何做人的抉择 请和我谈
lt was about my choices as a human being. Please.
是啊
Yeah.
你知道吗...
Well, you know...
我正好需要喝一杯
...l could sure use a drink, my friend.
“- 有些幻想、短暂 和难以捉摸”
''...but a little fantastic and fleeting and out of reach.''
然后呢？
Then what happens?
这是书的结尾
Well, that's the end of the book.
我希望以单纯方式表现...
l wanted to present it simply...
不用太宣染的角色特征 或惊悚的故事布局
...without big character arcs or sensationalizing the story.
我希望把花卉表现得 一如上帝的奇迹
l wanted to show flowers as God's miracles.
我要明说 欧琳没有见过鬼兰开花
l wanted to show that Orlean never saw the blooming ghost orchid.
那是一种失望之情
lt was about disappointment.
原来如此
l see.
那不是电影
That's not a movie.
你必须从头来过，加入戏剧成分
You gotta go back, put in the drama.
我已经不能回头，我写了一大堆 错误的开头和进展
l can't go back. l've got pages of false starts and wrong approaches.
- 交卷限期早就过了 - 我教你一招秘诀
- l'm way past my deadline. - l'll tell you a secret.
最后一幕定江山
A last act makes a film.
让观众在结局时大惊失色 你就成功了
Wow them in the end, and you got a hit.
可以有缺陷、有问题 但结尾一定要精彩...
You can have flaws, problems, but wow them in the end...
你就成功了
...and you've got a hit.
找一个结尾 但不能捏造
Find an ending. But don't cheat.
更不可以滥用解围人物
And don't you dare bring in a deus ex machina.
你的角色必须有所改变...
Your characters must change...
必须是他们自己的变化
...and the change must come from them.
那样做，就会很好
Do that and you'll be fine.
你保证？
You promise?
马契先生
Mr. McKee.
- 你以前是不是上过我的课？ - 那是我弟弟
- Have you taken my course before? - My brother did.
双胞胎弟弟，唐诺 是他怂恿我来的
My twin brother, Donald. He's the one who got me to come.
- 双胞胎编剧？ - 是的
- Twin screenwriters? - Yeah.
朱里士和菲利浦艾斯丁...
Well, Julius and Philip Epstein...
北非谍影的编剧...
...who wrote Casablanca...
- 就是一对双胞胎 - 你上课说过了
- ...they were twins - You mentioned that in class.
有史以来最棒的编剧
Finest screenplay ever written.
这里是大编剧住宅
Great writers' residence.
- 唐诺 - 嘿，旅途好吗？
- Donald. - Hey, how's your trip going?
你搭上女专栏作家了吗？ 你这色鬼
You getting it on with that lady journalist, you dog you?
是啊
Yeah.
我是要恭喜你的剧本
Listen, l'm just calling to say congratulations on your script.
是不是太棒了？马帝说要帮我 争取6位数高酬，而不是5位数
Isn't that cool? Marty says he can get me high- sixes against a mil- five.
真太好了，唐诺
That's great, Donald.
我要谢谢你的帮忙
l want to thank you for all your help.
我没帮什么忙
I wasn't any help.
还说呢 你让我住你的房子
Come on, you let me stay in your place.
你诚心待我 激励我努力的决心
And your integrity inspired me to even try.
简直像骑脱缰野马
lt's been a wild ride.
凯瑟琳说她想演凯西
Catherine says she wants to play Cassie.
噢，拜托
Oh, please!
求求你，唐诺？
Please, Donald?
凯瑟琳姬娜？
Catherine Keener?
- 凯瑟琳姬娜在我家？ - 是啊，我们在玩吹牛
- Catherine Keener's in my house? - Yeah, we're playing Boggle.
她真正点 你应该和她交往，查理
She's so great. You should really hang out with her, Charles.
好，听着...
Yeah. Look....
我在想
l've been thinking.
你愿意跟我在纽约待几天吗？
Maybe you'd be interested in hanging out with me for a few days in New York.
好啊，愿意
Oh, my God, yes.
是吗？
Yeah?
我要让一些人看剧本...
l was gonna show my script to some people...
你也可以看一下 如果你愿意
...and, well, maybe you could read it too, you know, if you like.
当然愿意，我很荣幸
Of course. I'd be flattered.
好
Okay.
谢了，查理
Thanks, Charles.
好的，再见
Okay, bye.
要是你会怎么做？
So, like, what would you do?
这剧本好像在开我玩笑？
The script kind of makes fun of me, huh?
- 对不起，我在尝试一些... - 嘿，我不介意，很好笑
- l'm sorry. l was trying something... - Hey, l don't mind. lt's funny.
好，好吧
Good. Okay.
那你会怎么做？
So, what would you do?
你和我很不相同，查理 我们的天份不一样
You and me are so different, Charles. We're different talents.
我知道，只是好玩...
l know. Just for fun...
伟大的唐诺会怎么写结局？
...how would the great Donald end this script?
闭嘴， “伟大的唐诺”
Shut up. ''The great Donald.''
我觉得你少了什么
l feel like you're missing something.
- 好吧，像是啥？ - 你看
- All right. Like what? - Look.
我在飞机上研究了一下
l did a little research on the airplane.
有时这类故事好像另有含义...
''Sometimes this kind of story turns out to be something more...
像是生命中的刹那扩张成...
...some glimpse of life that expands...
就像把日本纸球丢进水中...
...like those Japanese paper balls you drop in water...
让它张开成花 形状非常奇特...
...and they bloom into flowers and the flower is so marvelous...
你会不知不觉 看得入神...
...you can't believe there was a time all you saw in front of you...
忘怀了周遭的事物
...was a paper ball and a glass of water.''
第一，这根本矛盾 她说她并不喜欢花
Well, first of all, that's inconsistent. She said she didn't care about flowers.
- 你真是的，那只是一种比喻手法 - 好嘛，但比喻什么？
- For God's sake, it's just a metaphor. - Well, but for what?
是什么把纸球变成了花朵？ 书里并没有说，查理
What turned that paper ball into a flower? lt's not in the book, Charles.
- 我不知道，你在钻牛角尖 - 也许
- l don't know. You're reaching. - Maybe.
但我认为其实你应该见见她 去了解这个女的
But l think you actually need to speak to this woman. To know her.
我做不到
l can't.
- 真的 - 那我去
- Really. - l'll go.
我用你的名义去
l'll pretend l'm you.
我愿意这样做，查理
l want to do it, Charles.
我们的最终目的 是要医好你的电影，老哥
We'll get to the bottom of this. We're gonna fix your movie, bro.
但你必须跟我完全一样
But you've gotta be exactly me.
我要雇全我的名声
l have a reputation to maintain.
你不可以耍宝 你不可以黏人
You can't be a goofball. You can't be an asshole.
- 我不是黏人精啊 - 你知道我的意思
- l'm not an asshole. - You know what l mean.
不要打情骂俏，不说低俗笑话
No flirting. No bad jokes.
不要用你的傻笑
Don't laugh how you laugh.
我没有要笑 我会让人觉得我就是你
l'm not gonna laugh. l get to have people think l'm you.
人格保证
lt's an honor.
那我要开炮了
So l guess l'll bring out the big guns now.
你和老许保持联络吗？
Do you keep in touch with Laroche?
因为我觉得你在字里行间 对他很有好感，能否说明？
l felt l detected an attraction to him in the subtext. Care to comment?
其实，我们之间 纯粹只是业务公事
Well, our relationship was strictly reporter- subject.
的确这种关系 也会须要密切的接触
l mean, certainly an intimacy does evolve in this kind of relationship.
我是说，我对他述说的每件事 都很感兴趣
By definition, l was so interested in everything he had to say.
当然书写完了 这种关系也就结束了
But the relationship ends when the book ends.
- 睁眼说瞎话 - 什么？
- Mendacious deceit. - What?
没什么
Nothing.
最后一个问题
l just have one more question.
如果你能和历史人物共餐 古今皆可...
lf you could have dinner with one historical personage, living or dead...
你最想和哪两个？
...who would it be?
那我会说...
Well, l would have to say...
爱因斯坦
...Einstein.
或耶稣
Or Jesus.
很好
Very good.
有意思
lnteresting answer.
- 她说谎 - 为什么？
- She's lying. - What do you mean?
- 出了什么事？ - 没事，她全答对了
- What happened? - Nothing. She said everything right.
- 太准了 - 也许她说的都是实话
- Too right. - Well, maybe because they're true.
你有没有出我洋相？
Did you embarrass me?
答得太过精准的人都是骗子
People who answer questions too right are liars.
而且都会说耶稣和爱因斯坦 那是包装好的答案
And everybody says Jesus and Einstein. That's a prepackaged answer.
- “耶稣和爱因斯坦” ？ - 查理，我有个主意
- ''Jesus and Einstein''? - Listen, Charles, l have an idea.
你要帮我买一副望远镜
You'll need to buy me a pair of binoculars.
“耶稣和爱因斯坦”是什么意思？
What's ''Jesus and Einstein''?
一起来
Come on.
跟我一起唱
Sing with me.
你要望远镜做什么？
What the hell do you need binoculars for?
我们快过去
Let's go, let's go.
她挂了电话 有点恼
She hung up the phone. She's upset.
不要再看了 别理她了
Stop watching her. Leave her alone.
她哭了
She's crying.
她在用电脑
She's at her computer.
焦距可以调整
This is morally reprehensible.
联合航空...
United...
到迈阿密
...to Miami.
11点...
Eleven...
45分，明天早上
...fifty- five a.m. tomorrow.
- 我以为她和老许已经结束 - 她父母是住在佛罗里达
- l thought she was done with Laroche. - Her parents live in Florida.
那不是给爸妈的电话 老友
That was no parent phone call, my friend.
别叫我老友
Don't say ''my friend.''
有个男的进来了
A guy entering.
蛮帅的
Handsome.
应该是她丈夫
Must be her husband.
她对他有点怪怪的对不对？
She's acting weird with him, though, right?
你说呢？
Don't you think?
她在遮掩什么？
What's she hiding from him?
也许她是个蕾丝边 不知如何向他表白
Maybe she's a lesbian and doesn't know how to tell him.
你说呢？
What do you think?
你上过老许的色情网站吗？
Have you checked out Laroche's porn site?
没有，我在读书
No. l'm trying to read.
我倒想看看色情网站
Anyway, l'm gonna look at the porn site.
研究研究
Research.
- 不许你去告密 - 跟妈？
- Don't tell my old lady. - You mean Mom?
不是，我不是说妈
No, l don't mean Mom.
我还是觉得 明天应该去迈阿密
l still say we should go to Miami tomorrow.
休想
Forget it.
有些马子还不错
Some of these chicks look okay.
嘿，你猜怎地 明天应该去迈阿密
Hey, guess what. We're going to Miami tomorrow.
- 我说休想 - 我说要，宝贝，你来看
- l said, no. - l said, oh, yeah, baby. Come here.
迈阿密海滩
我渐渐了解改变是盲目的 不能任由选择
What I came to understand is that change is not a choice.
花种不能，我也不能
Not for a species of plant, and not for me.
改变径自发生，你就有了变化
It happens, and you are different.
法喀哈契，三年前
我和植物最大的差异...
Maybe the only distinction between the plant and me...
是在于 我隐瞒了我的变化
...is that afterward, I lied about my change.
我在书里撒了谎 我和丈夫虚情假意...
I lied in my book. I pretended with my husband...
假装一切还是老样子
...that everything was the same.
但那天在沼泽中 发生了一些事情
But something happened in the swamp that day.
嘿，瞧吧
Hey, look.
我说我会找到 法喀哈契之宝
l told you l'd find the jewel of the Fakahatchee.
那是一朵花
lt's a flower.
只是一朵花而已
Just a flower.
也可以据为己有
Well, might as well grab it.
只要我在这里
Long as l'm here.
噢，真是
Oh, man.
我的色情网站要发了
Boy, my porn site's gonna be big.
有些事情我没有告诉你...
Look, something l didn't tell you...
我要告诉你有关鬼兰 好吗？
...that l want to tell you about the ghost. Okay?
可能对你会有帮助
l think it might help you.
我刚开始经营苗圃时
l'd just started at the nursery.
有一晚我折回去拿东西
And I went back one night to pick up something.
他们用鬼兰来提炼迷幻药
They wanted the ghost just to extract the drug.
本来是用在祭典上的...
lt had been a ceremonial thing...
但年轻的一辈 喜欢沉溺在恍惚当中
...but the young guys, you know, they liked to get stoned.
所以马邱才会...？
So Matthew...?
- 他也在吸...？ - 当然
- He was one of the guys who...? - Sure.
马邱一天到晚用它 直到断货
Matthew lived on that shit till they ran out.
那一天他对我发痴
Because there was this one day he was fascinated by me.
对我的头发和我的哀伤着迷
By my hair and my sadness.
对了，那你就知道了 我就是要告诉你这个
Yeah, well, it does that. That's what l wanted to tell you.
我是说，也许你会喜欢，苏丝 它会让你更加迷人
l mean, l think you'd like it, Susie. lt seems to help people be fascinated.
我可以帮你提炼 我也会，我偷学的
You know, l can extract it for you. l know how. l watched.
我可能是唯一懂门道的白人
l'm probably the only white guy who knows.
我想要这样做，苏丝
l want to do this, Susie.
我对兰花已经没兴趣了，老许
l'm done with orchids, Laroche.
- 喂？ - 嗨
- Hello? - Hi.
是我啦
lt's John.
收到我的包裹没？
Did you get my package?
约翰？
John?
约翰！
John!
约翰
Johnny.
- 嘿，约翰？ - 怎样？
- Hey, John? - Yeah?
我现在很快乐
Very happy now.
我很高兴
Well, I'm glad.
非常快乐
Very happy.
你发这样个声音...？
Will you go like this...?
要继续
No. Keep going.
不对，不对
No. No.
我要发生一个拨号声 你要持续发出声音
l'm trying to make a dial tone. And you have to sustain.
然后我加入，一起出声...
And then l will join you, and together- -
- 我一个人做不来 - 你要我发哪一个声音？
- See, l can't do it by myself. - Which one do you want me to do?
- 对，对，对 - 好，开始
- Yes. Yes. Yes. - Okay. Here we go.
- 这就对了 - 我们成功了
- That's it. - We got it.
我们做到了，真好玩
We got it. That's fucking amazing.
你从不会寂寞吗？约翰
Do you ever get lonely sometimes, Johnny?
我是个怪孩子
Well, I was a weird kid.
没有人喜欢
Nobody liked me.
不过我在想...
But I had this idea...
如果我等久一点 也许有人会...
...if I waited long enough, someone would...
发现我...
...come around and just...
了解我
...you know, understand me.
就像我娘一般
Like my mom.
但是个别人
Except someone else.
她会静静望着我说
She'd look at me and quietly say:
“好的”
''Yes. ''
就像这样
Just like that.
于是我就不再孤单
And I wouldn't be alone anymore.
我希望自己是蚂蚁
l wish l were an ant.
它们容光焕发
They're so shiny.
你比任何蚂蚁更容光焕发
You're shinier than any ant, darling.
这是我听过最甜的赞美
That's the sweetest thing anybody has ever said to me.
嗯...
Well...
因为我喜欢你
...l like you, that's why.
佛罗里达，三年后
嘿
Hey.
我没那时间
l don't have time for that.
我走近一点去看，你等着
l'll get a closer look. You wait here.
等一下
No, wait!
我去
l should go.
我是说，这是我的事
l mean, it should be me, right?
我是说...
l mean...
该我...
...it's my....
- 我要... - 去吧，老哥
- l was, you know... - Go for it, bro.
你行的
You're the man.
撕开它
Rip them.
Just rip them.
亲爱的，我不知道是怎么了
Darling, l don't know what's come over you.
你上次热情如火 我也在的啊
You came all over me last time l was here, as l recall.
天杀的
Goddamn!
嘿！可恶
Hey! Fuck.
别跑！
Get in here!
闭嘴！ 坐下！
Shut the fuck up, now! Sit the fuck down!
- 是谁呀？ - 你是什么人？
- Who is that, Johnny? - Who the fuck are you?
我... 谁都不是
l just... Nobody.
- 我，我只是... - 等一下，等一下
- l just... l'm just... - Wait a minute, wait a minute.
他是那个编剧
He's that screenwriter.
- 那个改编我们书的人？ - 对
- The guy that's adapting our book? - Yeah.
这可玄了
Well, that's wild.
高兴认识你
lt's nice to meet you.
嘿，公子...
Hey, dude...
- 到底谁演我啊？ - 我不知道，我应该...
- ...who's gonna play me? - l don't know that. l should- -
我倒觉得应该由我自己来演
Well, l thought l should play me.
为什么...？
Why...?
- 他在跟踪我？ - 没有，当然不是，我该走了
- Did he follow me? - No, of course not. l should go.
我是说 很高兴认识你们...
Yeah, yeah. l mean, it was nice to meet you...
我把电话号码给你
...but let me give you my number.
我吓坏了，约翰 他为什么在这里？
l'm really freaking here, Johnny. Why is he here?
他为什么跟踪我？
Why did he follow me?
- 他知道多少？ - 我根本什么都不知道
- What does he know? - l don't know anything about anything.
- 他看见温室了 - 喔，糟糕
- He did see the greenhouse. - Oh, shit.
喔，糟糕
Oh, shit.
你要把这一切写进剧本吗？
Are you gonna write about this in your screenplay?
我根本么不着头绪
l really don't know what ''this'' is.
他扯谎
He's lying.
- 抓住他 - 别动...
- Hold him. - Stay! Just- -
我们必须做了他
We have to kill him.
- 什么？ - 不然要怎么办？
- What? - What are we supposed to do?
- 还能怎么办？ - 做好别动！
- What can we do? - Sit the fuck down!
苏丝...
Susie...
你要冷静下来
...you gotta calm down.
你太激动了
Now, you're getting a little emotional.
- 你不懂... - 我不能让他写我
- You don't know... - l can't have him writing about me.
我不要让全世界知道我们的事...
l can't have the whole world, all the people knowing about us...
以及这些
...and about this.
为什么？
Why?
- 你以我为耻吗？ - 不，不是这样
- You ashamed of me, Susie? - No, that's not it.
- 你怎会这么想？ - 那是...
- No. How can you even think of that? - Well- -
我是个专栏作家 而且喀药的事...
l'm a professional journalist, and the drugs and- -
我们不能杀人
We can't kill anyone.
好，好
Okay. Okay.
那我自己来
Then l'll do it.
我自己来
By myself.
- 苏丝... - 嘿！坐下别动！
- Susan... - Hey! Come on. Fucking get down!
- 我不会说出去... - 把他弄上车！
- l wouldn't tell any... - Put him in his fucking car!
法喀哈契浅滩 州立保育区
关掉引擎，下车
Turn it off. Just get out.
跑！快走！
Run! Run! Go!
苏丝！什么事？
Susan! What the fuck was that?
我不知道，我看不见
- l don't know. l couldn't see. - Shit. Fuck!
来！帮我找手电筒
Come on! Help me find the flashlight.
又有一个人？
So it was a guy?
对，很肥
Yeah. Fat.
我只知道这么多
That's all l could tell.
这太荒唐了 我们要分开来
This is ridiculous. We're gonna have to split up.
我不要自己一个人 我不要
l can't. l can't be by myself out here. l'm not gonna do that.
- 我们会被发现 - 不会
- They're gonna find us. - l don't think so.
我不想死，唐诺 我虚度一生，我虚度了
l don't want to die, Donald. l've wasted my life. God, l've wasted it.
- 你没有，也不会死 - 我虚度了
- You did not. And you're not gonna die. - l wasted it.
我佩服你，唐诺
l admire you, Donald, you know?
我一生木讷不仁 担心着别人对我的观感...
l spent my whole life paralyzed, worrying about what people think of me...
- 而你却毫不以为意 - 我才不是不以为意
- ...and you, you're just oblivious. - l'm not oblivious.
你不明白，我是在称赞你
No, you don't understand. l mean that as a compliment.
高中的时候有一次
There was this time in high school.
我在图书馆窗外看你...
l was watching you out the library window...
- 你正在和莎拉玛西谈话 - 我那时好爱她
- ...you were talking to Sarah Marsh. - Oh, God, l was so in love with her.
我知道，你们正在打情骂俏 而她对你百依百顺
l know. And you were flirting with her, and she was being really sweet to you.
- 我记得 - 后来，你走开后...
- l remember that. - And then, when you walked away...
她开始和金姆凯涅 开起你的玩笑
...she started making fun of you with Kim Canetti.
那就像他们在笑我自己
And it was like they were laughing at me.
而你好像全然不知？
You didn't know at all?
- 你似乎很快乐 - 其实我知道，我都听见了
- You seemed so happy. - l knew. l heard them.
那你为什么还能那么快乐？
Well, how come you were so happy?
我爱莎拉
l loved Sarah, Charles.
那是我的爱情
lt was mine, that love.
我拥有的
l owned it.
即使莎拉也无权否定
Even Sarah didn't have the right to take it away.
我可以爱我想爱的任何人
l can love whoever l want.
但她觉得你很可悲
But she thought you were pathetic.
那是她家的事，与我无关
That was her business, not mine.
你是施爱的人 谁爱你并不重要
You are what you love, not what loves you.
我早就下定这个决心
That's what l decided a long time ago.
你怎么了？
What's up?
谢谢你
Thank you.
谢啥？
For what?
别出声，嘘！
No, shh!
我听到他们了
Listen. l hear them.
我听到他们的呼吸
l hear them. l hear them breathing.
查理
Charlie?
- 查理？ - 查理！
- Charlie? - Charlie!
- 两位？ - 查理
- Guys? - Charlie!
查理！
Charlie!
车在哪？
Where's the van?
- 他们走了没？ - 不知道，也许吧
- Are they gone? - l don't know. Maybe.
约翰？约翰！
John? John!
可恶！
Shit!
我竟然中枪了 这太扯了吧？
l can't believe l got shot. lsn't that fucked up?
闭嘴，别笑
Shut up. Stop laughing.
唐诺？没事的 会没事的
Donald? You're gonna be okay. lt's gonna be okay, Donald.
别睡着，千万别睡 唐诺，看着我
Just don't go to sleep. Just don't go to sleep, Donald. Look at me.
看着我，唐诺 看着我
Look at me, Donald. Keep looking at me.
张开眼睛 唐诺，张开眼睛
Open your eyes. Donald, please open your eyes.
唐诺，拜托 张开眼睛
Donald. Donald, please open your eyes, Donald.
唐诺！张开眼睛
Donald! Donald, open your eyes!
看着我
Look at me.
救命！
Help!
约翰！
John!
停！
Halt!
对不起了
l'm sorry.
我不得已
Now l have to do this too.
我也没杀过人
l'm not a killer.
怪你自己...
You put yourself in- -
约翰！
Johnny!
- 救命！ - 不，不！
- Help! - No, no!
约翰！约翰！
Johnny! Johnny! John!
不，不...
Oh, no, no, no.
你这烂肥仔！
Oh, God. You fat piece of shit!
- 他死了，你这浑蛋！ - 闭嘴！
- He's dead, you loser! - Shut up!
- 你毁了我的人生，肥猪！ - 闭嘴！闭嘴！
- You ruined my life, you fat fuck! - Shut up! Shut up!
去你的，你只不过是个 孤单无望的可悲毒虫！
Fuck you, lady! You're just a lonely, old, desperate, pathetic drug addict!
我的天那
Oh, my God.
完了，一切都完了
lt's over. Everything's over.
全都做错了
l did everything wrong.
我要从头重新来过
l want my life back.
我要重新做人，免得太迟了
l want it back before it all got fucked up.
我要重新当小孩 我要重新来过
l want to be a baby again. l want to be new.
我要重新来过
l want to be new.
喂？
Hello?
- 喂？ - 妈
- Hello? - Mom.
查理？是你吗？
Charles? Charles, is that you?
查理，出了什么事？你没事吧？
Charles, what's the matter? You okay?
唐诺说 那是她家的事，与我无关
Donald says, ''That was her business, not mine.
你是施爱的人 谁爱你并不重要
You are what you love, not what loves you.
“我早就下定这个决心”
I decided that a long time ago. ''
考夫曼开始饮泣
Kaufman starts to cry.
他想要谢谢他弟弟 却说不出话来
He tries to thank his brother, but he can't put it into words.
- 你过得还好吗？ - 我很好
- So how you getting on? - l'm okay.
我想念他
l miss him, you know?
- 剧本进行得如何？ - 很顺利，快写完了
- How's the script coming? - lt's good. l'm almost finished.
真希望赶快换个跑道
l'll be really glad to move on to something else.
我了解
l'll bet.
你也过得好吗？
Things okay with you?
元月份，大卫和我要去布拉格 那是个重点
And then in January, David and l went to Prague. That was a high point.
- 太好了 - 那里的木偶戏很有名
- That sounds great. - There's amazing puppet theater there.
我听说了，一定要去看看
Yeah, l've heard. l've gotta see that.
还有个教堂 摆满了人的骷髅和骨头
And there's this church decorated with, like, human skulls and bones.
四万块骷髅和骨头
Forty thousand skulls and bones.
我到那里时有想到你
l thought about you when l went there.
查理，我在和别人交往 为什么还要吻我？
Charlie, l'm with someone. Why are you doing this now?
我爱你
l love you.
我该走了，我还有事...
l should go. l have to....
必须处理 周末就要动身了...
Stuff l have to do. l'm going away this weekend....
- 千头万续，真的 - 好
- Million things, okay? - Yeah.
我也爱你，你知道的
l love you too, you know.
我得赶快回家 我知道结局该怎么写了
I have to go right home. I know how to finish the script now.
考夫曼和艾咪吃完午饭 开车回家...
It ends with Kaufman driving home after his lunch with Amelia...
心里有了结局的点子
...thinking he knows how to finish the script.
糟糕，这是旁白 马契最反对旁白
Shit, that's voice- over. McKee would not approve.
还有什么方法来表现？ 天知道
How else can I show his thoughts? I don't know.
管他马契怎么说 我自己觉得很恰当
Well, who cares what McKee says? It feels right.
就这么决定
Conclusive.
不知道谁会演我 希望不要太肥
I wonder who's gonna play me. Someone not too fat.
我喜欢那个法国大鼻子 但受不了他的口音
I like that Gerard Depardieu, but can he not do the accent?
总之，完工了 真是太好了
Anyway, it's done. And that's something.
于是： 考夫曼和艾咪见过面 开车回家...
So: ''Kaufman drives off from his encounter with Amelia...
第一次，心里充满了希望
...filled for the first time with hope. ''
我喜欢
I like this.
这个好
This is good.
我们是一体的，警官 我终于了解到
如同身体里的细胞 看不到整个身体
就像鱼看不见海洋 因此我们互相艳羡，互相憎恨
彼此怨恨，真傻 心脏细胞恨着肺细胞
...摘自 “3”的凯西
永怀挚爱的唐诺考夫曼